<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101116175559|397141509" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="51885" pageid="51885" ns="0" title="Multiculturalism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-17T05:18:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=November 2009}}
'''Multiculturalism''' is the acceptance or promotion of multiple [[ethnic]] [[culture]]s, applied to the [[demographics|demographic make-up]] of a specific place, usually at the organizational level, e.g. [[school]]s, [[business]]es, [[neighborhood]]s, [[city|cities]] or [[nation]]s. In this context, multiculturalists advocate extending equitable status to distinct ethnic and [[religion|religious]] groups without promoting any specific [[ethnic]], [[religious]], and/or cultural community [[Value (personal and cultural)|values]] as central.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Multiculturalism Dictionary.Reference.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

The policy of multiculturalism is often contrasted with the concepts [[cultural assimilation|assimilationism]] and [[social integration]].

==Support for multiculturalism==
Multiculturalism is seen by its supporters as a fairer system that allows people to truly express who they are within a society, that is more tolerant and that adapts better to social issues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/mar/22/multiculturalism-blame-culture-segregation Guardian.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; They argue that culture is not one definable thing based on one race or religion, but rather the result of multiple factors that change as the world changes.

==Opposition to multiculturalism==
{{Main|Criticism of multiculturalism}}
When criticising multiculturalism, it is important to first define the term. Andrew Heywood distinguishes between two overall forms of multiculturalism: descriptive and normative. "The term ‘multiculturalism’ has been used in a variety of ways, both descriptive and normative. As a descriptive term, it has been taken to refer to cultural diversity … As a normative term, multiculturalism implies a positive endorsement, even celebration, of communal diversity, typically based on either the right of different groups to respect and recognition, or to the alleged benefits to the larger society of moral and cultural diversity”.&lt;ref&gt;Heywood, Political ideologies,4th edition, Palgrave Macmillan 2007: 313&lt;/ref&gt;

Criticism of multiculturalism often debates whether the multicultural ideal of benignly co-existing cultures that interrelate and influence one another, and yet remain distinct, is sustainable, paradoxical or even desirable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://stiffkitten.wordpress.com/2010/05/07/the-problem-of-normative-multiculturalism/ The problem of normative multiculturalism]&lt;/ref&gt; It is argued that [[Nation states]], who would previously have been synonymous with a distinctive cultural identity of their own, lose out to enforced multiculturalism and that this ultimately erodes the host nations distinct culture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/0000000CA4C4.htm Spiked-culture | Article | Backlash against multiculturalism?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/00000002D35E.htm Spiked-politics | Article | The trouble with multiculturalism&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4295318.stm Report attacks multiculturalism]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Susan Moller Okin]] wrote about this question in her essay "Is Multiculturalism Bad for Women?" (1999).&lt;ref&gt;Okin, [http://www.bostonreview.net/BR22.5/okin.html "Is Multiculturalism Bad for Women?"], ''Boston Review'' 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

Harvard professor of political science [[Robert D. Putnam]] conducted a nearly decade long study how multiculturalism affects social trust.&lt;ref name="Putnam, Robert D. 2007"&gt;Putnam, Robert D., "E Pluribus Unum: Diversity and Community in the Twenty-first Century -- The 2006 Johan Skytte Prize," ''Scandinavian Political Studies'' 30 (2), June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  He surveyed 26,200 people in 40 American communities, finding that when the data were adjusted for class, income and other factors, the more racially diverse a community is, the greater the loss of trust.  People in diverse communities "don’t trust the local mayor, they don’t trust the local paper, they don’t trust other people and they don’t trust institutions," writes Putnam.&lt;ref&gt;Sailer, Steve, [http://www.amconmag.com/article/2007/jan/15/00007/ "Fragmented Future,"] ''American Conservative'', Jan. 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In the presence of such ethnic diversity, Putnam maintains that

&lt;blockquote&gt;
[W]e hunker down. We act like turtles. The effect of diversity is worse than had been imagined. And it’s not just that we don’t trust people who are not like us. In diverse communities, we don’t trust people who do look like us.&lt;ref name="Putnam, Robert D. 2007"/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Ethologist [[Frank Salter]] writes:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Relatively homogeneous societies invest more in public goods, indicating a higher level of public altruism.  For example, the degree of ethnic homogeneity correlates with the government's share of gross domestic product as well as the average wealth of citizens.  Case studies of the United States, Africa and South-East Asia find that multi-ethnic societies are less charitable and less able to cooperate to develop public infrastructure.  Moscow beggars receive more gifts from fellow ethnics than from other ethnies [''sic''].  A recent multi-city study of municipal spending on public goods in the United States found that ethnically or racially diverse cities spend a smaller portion of their budgets and less per capita on public services than do the more homogenous cities.&lt;ref&gt;Salter, Frank, ''On Genetic Interests'', pg.146.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Different understandings of multiculturalism==
In contemporary society, multiculturalism is generally understood in two different and seemingly inconsistent ways:
*The first focuses on interaction and communication between different cultures. Interactions of cultures provide opportunities for the cultural differences to communicate and interact to create multiculturalism.
*The second centers on diversity and cultural uniqueness. Cultural isolation can protect the uniqueness of the local culture of a nation or area and also contribute to global cultural diversity. The policy “[[Cultural exception]]” introduced by France in General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) negotiations in 1993 was a precise example of  protecting one's own cultural safety. 

When different cultures operate with each other, those two understandings of multiculturalism result in dissimilar strategies - cultural interaction and isolation - and neither of them is absolutely right. The two understandings of multiculturalism are not absolutely distinct from each other. Moreover, the opposing understandings and strategies sometimes actually complement each other work to generate new cultural phenomena that embody the ideologies of the individual cultures and the relationships between them. The term “[[Transculturation]]”, coined by Cuban anthropologist Fernando Ortiz in 1940, indicates a transaction of one culture with another.&lt;ref&gt;Ortiz, Fernando. Cuban Counterpoint: Tobacco and Sugar, Durham, NC: Duke University Press,ISBN 0-8223-1616-1. Trans. Harriet de Onís.1995&lt;/ref&gt;. Mary Louise Pratt coined the phrase “the contact zone” to describe cultural clashes and operations.&lt;ref&gt;Pratt, Mary Lousis. "Arts of the Contact Zone." From Inquiry to Academic Writing: a Text and Reader. Boston: Bedford/St. Martin's, 2008. 355-68.&lt;/ref&gt; In the cultural environment they illustrated, cultures are not only interacted or isolated. Those two strategies work at the same time and apply to different aspects of cultures to create new forms of cultures. Multiculturalism can be defined in a ways that go beyond human activities to give a vivid multi-dimensional understanding of cultural interaction, cultural isolation and  phenomena between these two extremes.

==Multiculturalism in contemporary Western society==
[[Image:Outside Union Station.jpg|thumb|upright|''Monument to Multiculturalism'' by Francesco Pirelli in [[Toronto]], [[Canada]]. Four identical sculptures are located in [[Buffalo City Local Municipality|Buffalo City]], [[South Africa]]; [[Changchun]], [[China]]; [[Sarajevo]], [[Bosnia]] and [[Sydney]], [[Australia]].]]
Multiculturalism was adopted as official policy, in several [[Western world|Western]] nations from the 1970s onward, for reasons that varied from country to country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unesco.org/most/pp4.htm Policy Paper no. 4 - Multiculturalism: New Policy Responses to Diversity]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pch.gc.ca/pgm/ai-ia/rir-iro/gbll/divers/index-eng.cfm Multiculturalism in Canada ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www4.gu.edu.au/ext/civics/cv02/mod03/cv02m03t02.htm Immigration and Multiculturalism]&lt;/ref&gt; The great cities of the Western world are increasingly made of a mosaic of
cultures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unu.edu/dialogue/papers/claval-s2.pdf Multiculturalism and the Dynamics of Modern Civilizations]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Ortodoxsp.JPG|thumb|230px|[[orthodox church|Orthodox]] Cathedral in [[Sao Paulo]]. Brazilian [[megalópolis]] is an example of multicultural city.]]

===Multiculturalism as introductory to monoculturalism===
[[Image:Hk anti-discrimination poster.jpg|thumb|right|250px|An anti-discrimination poster in a [[Hong Kong]] [[MTR|subway]] station. Circa. 2005]]
Multiculturalism, as generally understood, refers to a theoretical approach and a number of policies adopted in Western [[nation-state]]s, which had seemingly achieved a de facto single national identity during the 18th and/or 19th centuries. Many nation-states in Africa, Asia, and the Americas are culturally diverse, and are 'multi-cultural' in a [[descriptive]] sense. In some, [[communalism]] is a major political issue. The policies adopted by these states often have parallels with multicultural-ist policies in the [[Western world]], but the historical background is different, and the goal may be a mono-cultural or mono-ethnic [[nation-building]] - for instance in the Malaysian government's attempt to create a 'Malaysian race' by 2020.&lt;ref&gt;[[The Economist]]: ''[http://www.economist.com/surveys/displayStory.cfm?story_id=1677228 The changing of the guard]'', April 3rd 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
{{Main|Multiculturalism in Canada}}
[[Image:German immigrants, Quebec City, Canada, 1911.jpg|thumb|left|German immigrants in [[Quebec City]] in 1911]]
Immigration to Canada is driven by [[Economic impact of immigration to Canada|economic policy]] and [[Immigration to Canada#Immigration categories|family reunification]]. In 2001, approximately 250,640 people immigrated to [[Canada]]. The newcomers settle mostly in the major urban areas of [[Toronto]], [[Vancouver]] and [[Montreal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
  | url = http://www.statcan.gc.ca/pub/91-214-x/2008000/part-partie1-eng.htm
  | title = Section 1: Census metropolitan areas
  | work = Annual Demographic Estimates
  | publisher = [[Statistics Canada]]
  | date = 1 July 2009
  | accessdate = 2010-04-04
  | quote = As in prior years, the Toronto CMA was the first destination for international immigrants, 92,652 of whom moved to the Canadian metropolis. It was followed by the Montréal (38,898) and Vancouver (33,021) CMAs.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1990s and 2000s, the largest component of Canada’s immigrants came from [[Asia]], including the Middle East, South Asia, South-East Asia and East Asia.&lt;ref name = "migrate-Inflow"&gt;[http://www.migrationinformation.org/datahub/countrydata/country.cfm Inflow of foreign-born population by country of birth, by year]&lt;/ref&gt; Canadian society is often depicted as being very progressive, diverse, and multicultural. Accusing a person of racism in Canada is usually considered a serious slur.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last = Fontaine|first = Phil|author-link = Phil Fontaine|url = http://www.queensu.ca/sps/conferences_events/lectures/donald_gow/98lecture.pdf|format=PDF|title = Modern Racism in Canada by Phil Fontaine|publisher = Queen's University|date = April 24, 1998|postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Canadian political parties are now cautious about criticizing their country's high level of immigration, because, as noted by the [[Globe and Mail]], "in the early 1990s, the old [[Reform Party of Canada|Reform Party]] was branded 'racist' for suggesting that immigration levels be lowered from 250,000 to 150,000."&lt;ref name=Globevolpe&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/Page/document/v4/sub/MarketingPage?user_URL=http://www.theglobeandmail.com%2Fservlet%2Fstory%2FRTGAM.20051212.wxsmart12%2FBNStory%2FspecialDecision2006%2F&amp;ord=1155737424463&amp;brand=theglobeandmail&amp;force_login=true Is the current model of immigration the best one for Canada?], [[Globe and Mail]], 12 December 2005, URL accessed 16 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Canflagcartoon.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Political cartoon on Canada's multicultural identity, from 1911]]

===Argentina===
{{Main|Demographics of Argentina}}
Though not called ''Multiculturalism'' as such, the [[Constitution of Argentina#Preamble|preamble]] of Argentina's constitution explicitly promotes [[Immigration to Argentina|immigration]], and recognizes the individual's [[multiple citizenship]] from other countries. Though 97% of Argentina's population self-identify as of [[European ethnic groups|European descent]]&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;[http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Argentina.html Argentina]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="CIA"&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ar.html CIA - The World Factbook - Argentina]&lt;/ref&gt;  to this day a high level of multiculturalism remains a feature of the [[Argentine Culture|Argentine's culture]],&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.argentina.ar/_en/culture/ Argentine Culture Rich and Diverse]&lt;/ref&gt; allowing foreign festivals and holidays (e.g. [[Saint Patrick's Day]]), supporting all kinds of art or cultural expression from [[ethnic groups]], as well as their diffusion through an important multicultural presence in the media; for instance it is not uncommon to find newspapers&lt;ref&gt;*[http://www.buenosairesherald.com/ Buenos Aires Herald, Argentine-English language newspaper]&lt;/ref&gt; or radios programs in English, German, Italian or French in Argentina.

===Australia===
{{Main|Multiculturalism in Australia}}
The other country to have most fully adopted Canadian-style multiculturalism is Australia, with many similar policies, for example the formation of the [[Special Broadcasting Service]].&lt;ref name="immi.gov.au"&gt;[http://www.immi.gov.au/media/publications/research/_pdf/poa-2008.pdf IMMI.gov.au]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the 2006 census more than one fifth of the population were born overseas.&lt;ref name="immi.gov.au"/&gt; Furthermore, almost 50% of the population were either:

1. born overseas; or

2. had one or both parents born overseas.&lt;ref name="immi.gov.au"/&gt;

In terms of net migration per capita, Australia is ranked 18th (2008 Data) ahead of Canada, the USA and most of Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationmaster.com/graph/imm_net_mig_rat-immigration-net-migration-rate#definition Nationmaster.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
In the United States, multiculturalism is not clearly established in policy at the federal level.

[[Image:Mulberry Street NYC c1900 LOC 3g04637u edit.jpg|thumb|Mulberry Street, along which Manhattan's [[Little Italy, Manhattan|Little Italy]] is centered. [[Lower East Side, Manhattan|Lower East Side]], circa 1900.]]
In the United States, continuous mass immigration had been a feature of economy and society since the first half of the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hasia Diner]], [http://usinfo.state.gov/journals/itsv/0208/ijse/diner.htm "Immigration and U.S. History"], ''eJournal USA'', February 2008{{Dead link|date=September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The absorption of the stream of immigrants became, in itself, a prominent feature of America's [[national myth]]. The idea of the [[Melting pot]] is a [[metaphor]] that implies that all the immigrant cultures are mixed and amalgamated without state intervention.&lt;ref&gt;Zangwil, Israel. ''The Melting Pot,'' 1908.&lt;/ref&gt; The Melting Pot implied that each individual immigrant, and each group of immigrants, assimilated into American society at their own pace which, as defined above, is not multiculturalism as this is opposed to assimilation and integration. An Americanized (and often stereotypical) version of the original nation's cuisine, and its holidays, survived.
The Melting Pot tradition co-exists with a belief in national unity, dating from the [[Founding Fathers of the United States|American founding fathers]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
"Providence has been pleased to give this one connected country to one united people&amp;nbsp;— a people descended from the same ancestors, speaking the same language, professing the same religion, attached to the same principles of government, very similar in their manners and customs... This country and this people seem to have been made for each other, and it appears as if it was the design of Providence, that an inheritance so proper and convenient for a band of brethren, united to each other by the strongest ties, should never be split into a number of unsocial, jealous, and alien sovereignties."&lt;ref&gt;[[John Jay]], ''First American Supreme Court Chief Justice'', [[Federalist No. 2|Federalist Paper No. 2]]'''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

As a [[philosophy]], multiculturalism began as part of the [[pragmatism]] movement at the end of the nineteenth century in [[Europe]] and the United States, then as political and cultural [[pluralism]] at the turn of the twentieth. It was partly in response to a new wave of European imperialism in sub-Saharan Africa and the massive immigration of Southern and Eastern Europeans to the United States and [[Latin America]]. Philosophers, psychologists and historians and early sociologists such as [[Charles Sanders Peirce]], [[William James]], [[George Santayana]], [[Horace Kallen]], [[John Dewey]], [[W. E. B. Du Bois]] and [[Alain Locke]] developed concepts of [[cultural pluralism]], from which emerged what we understand today as multiculturalism. In ''Pluralistic Universe'' (1909), William James espoused the idea of a "plural society."  James saw pluralism as "crucial to the formation of philosophical and social [[humanism]] to help build a better, more egalitarian society.&lt;ref name = Boening&gt;{{cite news
  | last =Boening
  | first = Astrid B.
  | coauthors = 
  | title = Euro-Islam&amp;nbsp;– A Constructivist Idea or a Concept of the English School?
  | newspaper = European Union Miami Analysis (EUMA)
  | location =
  | volume =4
  | issue =12
  | pages =3–10
  | publisher =Miami-Florida European Union Center of Excellence
  | date =May 2007
  | url =http://www.miami.edu/eucenter/Boening_EuroIslam_EUMA2007edi.pdf
  | format =pdf
  | accessdate =30 September 2009 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
Multicultural policies were adopted by local administrations from the 1970s and 1980s onwards, in particular by the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour government]] of [[Tony Blair]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/columnists/minette_marrin/article6898174.ece Timesonline.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/mar/17/multiculturalism-diversity-political-policy Guardian.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; In national policy, legislation includes ''Race Relations Act'' and the ''British Nationality Act'' of 1948.
Most of the immigrants of the last decades came from the [[Indian subcontinent]] or the [[Caribbean]], i.e. from former [[British overseas territories|British colonies]]. In 2004 the number of people who became British citizens rose to a record 140,795&amp;nbsp;— a rise of 12% on the previous year. This number had risen dramatically since 2000. The overwhelming majority of new citizens come from Africa (32%) and Asia (40%), the largest three groups being people from [[Pakistan]], [[India]] and [[Somalia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4706862.stm BBC Thousands in UK citizenship queue]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Western world|Western]] English-speaking countries, multiculturalism as an official national policy started in Canada in 1971, followed by Australia in 1973.&lt;ref name = Bissoondath&gt;Bissoondath, Neil. 2002.  ''Selling Illusions: The Myth of Multiculturalism''. Toronto: Penguin. ISBN 978-0-14-100676-5.&lt;/ref&gt; It was quickly adopted as official policy by most member-states of the [[European Union]].  Recently, right-of-center governments in several European states—notably the [[Netherlands]] and [[Denmark]]— have reversed the national policy and returned to an official monoculturalism.&lt;ref name = Bissoondath /&gt; A similar reversal is the subject of debate in the United Kingdom, among others, due to evidence of incipient segregation and anxieties over "home-grown" [[terrorism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.workpermit.com/news/2005_04_26/uk/uk_immigration_debate.htm Fact or fiction in the great UK immigration debate]. workpermit.com. News. April 26, 2005. Retrieved on: October 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Continental Europe===
[[Image:Austria Hungary ethnic.svg|thumb|Ethno-linguistic map of [[Austria–Hungary]], 1910. [[Ethnic nationalism]] became the paramount issue as Italians, Slavs and Hungarians resisted rule by the German-dominated Habsburg state.]]
[[Image:Poland1937linguistic.jpg|thumb|Ethno-linguistic map of the [[Second Polish Republic]], 1937. The Polish-Ukrainian animosity grew into [[Massacres of Poles in Volhynia|ethnic massacres]] of 1943-44 in which up to 100,000 Poles died.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3057243.stm Poland and Ukraine resolve massacre row]". BBC News. July 11, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Presa clujeana.JPG|thumb|right|[[Hungarian language|Hungarian]] and [[Romanian language|Romanian]] language newspapers published in [[Cluj]] ([[Transylvania]], [[Romania]]).]]

Historically, Europe has always been polycultural—a mixture of Latin, Slavic, Germanic and Celtic cultures influenced by the importation of Hebraic, Hellenic and even Muslim belief systems; although the continent was supposedly unified by the super-position of Roman Catholic Christianity, it is accepted that geographic and cultural differences continued from antiquity into the modern age.
 {{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

Especially in the 19th century, the ideology of [[nationalism]] transformed the way Europeans thought about the [[Sovereign state|state]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} Existing states were broken up and new ones created; the new [[nation-states]] were founded on the principle that each [[nation]] is entitled to its own [[sovereignty]] and to engender, protect, and preserve its own unique culture and history. Unity, under this ideology, is seen as an essential feature of the nation and the nation-state—unity of descent, unity of culture, unity of language, and often unity of religion. The nation-state constitutes a culturally [[wiktionary:Homogeneity|homogeneous]] society, although some national movements recognized regional differences.

Where cultural unity was insufficient, it was encouraged and enforced by the state. The 19th-century nation-states developed an array of policies—the most important was compulsory [[primary education]] in the [[national language]]. The language itself was often standardized by a linguistic academy, and regional languages were ignored or suppressed. Some nation-states pursued violent policies of [[cultural assimilation]] and even [[ethnic cleansing]].

Some European Union countries have introduced policies for "social cohesion", "integration", and (sometimes) "assimilation". The policies include:
*compulsory courses and/or tests on [[historiography and nationalism|national history]], on the [[constitution]] and the [[legal system]] (e.g., the computer-based test for individuals seeking naturalization in the UK named [[Life in the United Kingdom test]])
*introduction of an official national history, such as the national [[Western canon|canon]] defined for the Netherlands by the [[Frits van Oostrom|van Oostrom]] Commission,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.entoen.nu/ Official Web site]&lt;/ref&gt; and promotion of that history (e.g., by exhibitions about [[Folk hero|national heroes]])
*tests designed to elicit "unacceptable" values. In [[Baden-Württemberg]] immigrants are asked what they would do if their son says he is a [[Homosexuality|homosexual]]. (The expected answer is that they would accept it).&lt;ref&gt;BBC report at [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4655240.stm News.BBC.co.uk], full list of questions in German at [http://www.taz.de/index.php?id=archivseite&amp;dig=2006/01/04/a0154 TAZ.de]&lt;/ref&gt;
*prohibitions on [[hijab|Islamic dress]]&amp;nbsp;— especially the [[niqab]] (often misnamed as [[burqa]]).&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/nov/11/religion.uk Netherlands moves toward total ban on Muslim veils]'', Guardian, November 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Netherlands===
{{Main|Multiculturalism in the Netherlands}}
In the 1950s, the [[Netherlands]] was generally a mono-ethnic and monocultural society: it was not explicitly [[monolingualism|monolingual]], but almost everyone could speak standard [[Dutch language|Dutch]]; [[Frisian languages|Frisian]], [[Limburgish]] and [[Dutch Low Saxon]] were the only indigenous minority languages. Its inhabitants shared a classic national identity, with a national [[mythos]] emphasizing the [[Dutch Golden Age]], and national heroes such as Admiral [[Michiel de Ruyter]]. Dutch society was segmented along religious and ideological lines, sometimes coinciding with differences in social class and lifestyle. This segmentation had developed since the late 19th century into a uniquely Dutch version, called [[pillarization]], enabling peaceful cooperation between the leaders of the various "pillars", while their constituencies remained largely segregated. This [[segregation]] is regarded{{bywhom?|date=October 2010}} as the reason for politicians [[Pim Fortuyn]] and [[Geert Wilders]] political success in the [[2000s]].

===Russia===
Because of colonialism and the gradual accretion of land over several centuries, Russia has over 150 different ethnic groups. Tensions between ethnic groups, particularly in the Caucasus region, have occasionally escalated into armed conflicts.

===Belgium===
In this field, Belgium shows the huge differences between multiculturalism and [[interculturalism]]. In the Flemish part, [[Flanders]], the official policy (which is supported by all main political parties except for one extreme-right party) is clearly inter-culturalist. The French-speaking parties however are very much multiculturalist.

===Germany===
Angela Merkel has stated that [[Multikulti]], the German term, has been a failure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Merkel says German multicultural society has failed|work= BBC|date=October 17, 2010|url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-11559451|accessdate=2010-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Germans argue over integration|work= BBC|date=November 30, 2004|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/4056109.stm|accessdate=2010-10-18|first=Ray|last=Furlong}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Multiculturalism in contemporary Eastern society==
===India===

The  culture of India has been shaped by its long history, unique geography and diverse demography. India's languages, religions, dance, music, architecture and customs differ from place to place within the country, but nevertheless possess a commonality. The culture of India is an amalgamation of these diverse sub-cultures spread all over the Indian subcontinent and traditions that are several millennia old.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  |last = Mohammada
  |first = Malika
  |title = The foundations of the composite culture in India
  |publisher = Aakar Books, 2007
  |issn = 8189833189, 9788189833183}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Religiously, [[Hindus]] form the majority, followed by Muslims. The actual statistics are: [[Hindu]] (80.5%), [[Muslim]] (13.4%), [[Christian]] (2.3%), [[Sikh]] (2.1%), [[Buddhist]], [[Bahá'í Faith in India|Bahá'í]], [[Ahmadiyya Muslim Community|Ahmadi]], [[Jain]], [[Jew]] and [[Parsi people|Parsi]] populations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.censusindia.gov.in/ Indian Census]&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Republic of India]]'s state boundaries are largely drawn based on linguistic groups; this decision led to the preservation and continuation of local ethno-linguistic cultures. Thus, states differ from one another in [[languages of India|language]], [[culture of India|culture]], [[Indian cuisine|cuisine]], clothing, literary style, [[architecture of India|architecture]], [[music of India|music]] and festivities. See [[Culture of India]] for more information.

===Indonesia===
There are more than 700 living languages spoken in Indonesia&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ethnologue.com/show_country.asp?name=indonesia Ethnologue report for Indonesia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and although predominantly Muslim the country also has large Christian and Hindu populations. Indonesia's national motto, "Bhinneka tunggal ika" ("Unity in Diversity" lit. "many, yet one"), articulates the diversity that shapes the country. Due to migration within Indonesia (as part of government [[transmigration program]]s or otherwise), there are significant populations of ethnic groups who reside outside of their traditional regions. Soon after [[Abdurrahman Wahid]] came into power in 1999, he quickly abolished some of the discriminatory laws in efforts to improve race relationships. [[Chinese Indonesian]]s are now in the era of rediscovery. Many younger generations, who cannot speak Mandarin due to the ban decades earlier, choose to learn Mandarin, as many learning centers open throughout the country. The [[Ambon, Maluku]] was the site of some of the worst violence between Christian and Muslim groups that gripped the [[Maluku Islands]] between 1999 and 2002.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/2243896.stm Religious violence erupts in Moluccas], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
[[Ethnic issues in Japan|Japanese society]], with its ideology of [[Monoculturalism|homogeneity]], has traditionally rejected any need to recognize ethnic differences in Japan, even as such claims have been rejected by such ethnic minorities as the Ainu.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Abe fine with 'homogeneous' remark|url=http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20070227a9.html|publisher=Kyodo News|date=2007-02-27|accessdate=2009-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese Minister [[Taro Aso]] has called Japan a “one race” nation.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/member/member.html?nn20051018a7.htm Aso says Japan is nation of 'one race']". The Japan Times. October 18, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; However, there are "International Society" NPOs funded by local governments throughout Japan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tokyo-international.org/ International Societies in Japan]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Malaysia===
{{Main|Ketuanan Melayu}}
[[Malaysia]] is a multiethnic country, with [[Malay (ethnic group)|Malays]] making up the majority, close to 52% of the population. About 30% of the population are [[Chinese Malaysian|Malaysians of Chinese descent]]. [[Indian Malaysian|Malaysians of Indian descent]] comprise about 8% of the population. The remaining 10% comprises:
* Native [[East Malaysia]]ns, namely [[Bajau]], [[Bidayuh]], [[Dusun]], [[Iban]], [[Kadazan]], [[Melanau]], [[Orang Ulu]], [[Sarawakian Malay]]s, etc.
* Other native tribes of [[Peninsular Malaysia]], such as the [[Orang Asli]] and Siamese people, and
* Non-native tribes of Peninsular Malaysia such as the [[Chettiar]]s, the [[Peranakan]] and the Portuguese.

The [[Malaysian New Economic Policy]] or NEP serves as a form of affirmative action (see [[Bumiputera (Malaysia)|Bumiputera]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/6237328.stm Malaysia fury at EU envoy remarks], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt; It promotes structural changes in various aspects of life from education to economic to social integration. Established after the [[May 13 Incident|May 13 racial riots]] of 1969, it sought to address the significant imbalance in the economic sphere where the minority [[Han Chinese|Chinese]] population had substantial control over commercial activity in the country.

The [[Malay Peninsula]] has a long history of international trade contacts, influencing its ethnic and religious composition. Predominantly [[Malays (ethnic group)|Malays]] before the 18th century, the ethnic composition changed dramatically when the British introduced new industries, and imported Chinese and Indian labor. Several regions in the then [[British Malaya]] such as [[Penang]], [[Malacca]] and [[Singapore]] became Chinese dominated. Co-existence between the three ethnicities (and other minor groups) was largely peaceful, despite the fact the immigration affected the demographic and cultural position of the Malays.

Preceding independence of the [[Federation of Malaya]], a [[social contract (Malaysia)|social contract]] was negotiated as the basis of a new society. The contract as reflected in the [[Constitution of Malaysia|1957 Malayan Constitution and the 1963 Malaysian Constitution]] states that the immigrant groups are granted citizenship, and Malays' special rights are guaranteed. This is often referred to the [[Bumiputra]] policy.

These [[Pluralism (political philosophy)|pluralist]] policies have come under pressure from racialist Malay parties, who oppose perceived subversion of Malay rights. The issue is sometimes related to the controversial [[status of religious freedom in Malaysia]].

===Mauritius===
Multiculturalism is a characteristic feature of the island of [[Mauritius]]. Mauritian society includes people from many different ethnic and religious groups: Hindu, Muslim and Sikh [[Indo-Mauritian]]s, [[Mauritian Creole people|Mauritian Creoles]] (of African and [[Malagasy people|Malagasy]] descent), Buddhist and Roman Catholic [[Sino-Mauritian]]s and [[Franco-Mauritian]]s (descendants of the original [[French people|French]] colonists).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infomauritius.com/ Some facts about Mauritius]&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Philippines===
The [[Philippines]] is the 8th most multiethnic nation in the world.&lt;ref&gt;The [[Philippines]] ranks 8th among 240 countries in terms of ethnic diversity. YEOH Kok Kheng, ''[http://www.fep.um.edu.my/working%20papers/2001/FEA-WP-2001-003.pdf Towards an Index of Ethnic Fractionalization]'', Table 1.&lt;/ref&gt; It has 10 distinct major indigenous ethnic groups mainly the [[Bicolano people|Bicolano]], [[Ibanag people|Ibanag]], [[Ilocano people|Ilocano]], [[Ivatan people|Ivatan]], [[Kapampangan people|Kapampangan]], [[Moro (ethnic group)|Moro]], [[Pangasinense people|Pangasinense]], [[Sambal people|Sambal]], [[Tagalog people|Tagalog]] and [[Visayan people|Visayan]]. The Philippines also has several aboriginal races such as the [[Bajau|Badjao]], [[Igorot]], [[Lumad]], [[Mangyan]] and [[Negritos]]. The country also has considerable communities of [[American settlement in the Philippines|American]], [[Arab settlement in the Philippines|Arabic]], [[Chinese Filipinos|Chinese]], [[Hinduism in the Philippines|Indian]] and [[Filipinos of Spanish descent|Hispanic]] descent and many more. The Philippine government has various programs supporting and preserving the nation's ethnic diversity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2794.htm State.gov]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Singapore===
Singapore recognizes three other languages, namely, [[Mandarin Chinese]], [[Tamil language|Tamil]] and [[Malay language|Malay]] as its official languages, with [[Malay language|Malay]] being the national language. Besides being a [[multilingualism|multilingual]] country, Singapore also acknowledges festivals celebrated by these three ethnic communities.

Areas which are enclaves containing a large population of certain ethnic groups exist in areas such as [[Chinatown, Singapore|Chinatown]], [[Geylang]] and [[Little India, Singapore|Little India]] in Singapore.

===South Korea===
[[South Korea]] is among the world's most ethnically homogeneous nations.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://aparc.stanford.edu/news/koreas_ethnic_nationalism_is_a_source_of_both_pride_and_prejudice_according_to_giwook_shin_20060802/ Korea's ethnic nationalism is a source of both pride and prejudice, according to Gi-Wook Shin]". The Korea Herald. August 2, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Those who do not share such features are often rejected by the Korean society or face discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.usc.edu/dept/LAS/CMTS/MonoPaper3-13.html The Life Instability of Intermarried Japanese Women in Korea]", Eung-Ryul Kim (Korea University and University of Southern California, The Center for Multiethnic and Transnational Studies)&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the word "multiculturalism" is increasingly heard in South Korea. In 2007, Han Geon-Soo, Professor of Cultural Anthropology at [[Kangwon National University]], published an article entitled "Multicultural Korea: Celebration or Challenge of Multiethnic Shift in Contemporary Korea?", noting: "As the increase of foreign migrants in Korea transforms a single-ethnic homogenous Korean society into multiethnic and multicultural one, Korean government and the civil society pay close attention to multiculturalism as an alternative value to their policy and social movement." He argued, however, that "the current discourses and concerns on multiculturalism in Korea" lacked "the constructive and analytical concepts for transforming a society".&lt;ref&gt;Han Geon-Soo, "Multicultural Korea: Celebration or Challenge of Multiethnic Shift in Contemporary Korea?", ''Korea Journal'', Vol.47 No.4, Winter 2007, pp.32-63&lt;/ref&gt; 

The same year, Stephen Castles of the International Migration Institute argued:
:''"Korea no longer has to decide whether it wants to become a multicultural society. It made that decision years ago – perhaps unconsciously – when it decided to be a full participant in the emerging global economy. It confirmed that decision when it decided to actively recruit foreign migrants to meet the economic and demographic needs of a fast-growing society. Korea is faced by a different decision today: what type of multicultural society does it want to be?"''&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Castles, [http://www.imi.ox.ac.uk/pdfs/SC%20paper%20on%20MC%20soc%20for%20GHFR%20Korea%202007.pdf "Will Labour Migration lead to a Multicultural Society in Korea?", Global Human Resources Forum 2007 / International Migration Institute&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Korea Times]]'' suggested in 2009 that South Korea was likely to become a multicultural society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.koreatimes.co.kr/www/news/biz/2010/10/123_57884.html "Multiculturalism Likely to Prevail in Korea"], Lee Hyo-sik, ''Korea Times'', December 24, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, ''[[JoongAng Daily]]'' reported: "Media in Korea is abuzz with the new era of multiculturalism. With more than one million foreigners in Korea, 2 percent of the population comes from other cultures." It added:
:''"If you stay too long, Koreans become uncomfortable with you. [...] Having a 2 percent foreign population unquestionably causes ripples, but having one million temporary foreign residents does not make Korea a multicultural society. [...] In many ways, this homogeneity is one of Korea’s greatest strengths. Shared values create harmony. Sacrifice for the nation is a given. Difficult and painful political and economic initiatives are endured without discussion or debate. It is easy to anticipate the needs and behavior of others. It is the cornerstone that has helped Korea survive adversity. But there is a downside, too. [...] Koreans are immersed in their culture and are thus blind to its characteristics and quirks. Examples of group think are everywhere. Because Koreans share values and views, they support decisions even when they are obviously bad. Multiculturalism will introduce contrasting views and challenge existing assumptions. While it will undermine the homogeneity, it will enrich Koreans with a better understanding of themselves."&lt;ref&gt;[http://joongangdaily.joins.com/article/view.asp?aid=2925120 "Multiculturalism in Korea"], ''JoongAng Daily'', August 26, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|cols=3}}
* [[Criticism of multiculturalism]]
* [[ACE Foundation]]
* [[Before Columbus Foundation]]
* [[Cosmopolitanism]]
* [[Cross-culturalism]]
* [[Cultural competence]]
* [[Cultural diversity in the media in Europe]]
* [[Cultural mosaic]]
* [[Cultural pluralism]]
* [[Ethnic origin]]
* [[Ethnocentrism]]
* [[Europeanism]]
* [[Global Centre for Pluralism]] (Canada)
* [[Global justice]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Interculturalism]]
* [[Miscegenation]]
* ''[[Multiculturalism without Culture]]'' (book)
* [[Multikulti]]
* [[Multinational state]]
* [[Nation-building]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Plural society]]
* [[Political correctness]]
* [[Polyethnicity]]
* [[Psi Sigma Phi]] Multicultural Fraternity, Incorporated
* [[Racial integration]]
* [[Societalism]]
* Society for the Study of [[Multi-Ethnic Literature of the United States]] (MELUS)
* [[Teaching for social justice]]
* [[Transculturation]]
* ''[[Unrooted Childhoods: Memoirs of Growing up Global]]'' (book)
* [[Whiteness studies]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last= Ankerl |first= Guy |title= Global communication without universal civilization (Coexisting contemporary civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western) |origyear= 2000 |series= INU societal research |volume= 1|publisher= INU Press |location= Geneva |isbn= 2-88155-004-5 |pages=|year= 2000 }}
* Ankerl, Guy. ''Coexisting Contemporary Civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western''. INU Press, Geneva 2000, ISBN 2 88155 004 5 .
* Bidmead, Andrew 'The Last of England' Legend Press 2010 ISBN 9781907461330
* Ellis, Frank . [http://www.amren.com/mtnews/archives/2009/05/multiculturalis.php Multiculturalism and Marxism] American Renaissance, November 1999
* Barzilai, Gad. (2003). ''Communities and Law: Politics and Cultures of Legal Identities.'' (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press).
* Chiu, C.-Y. &amp; Lueng, A. (2007). [http://www.in-mind.org/special-issue/do-multicultural-experiences-make-people-more-creative-if-so-2.html Do Multicultural Experiences Make People More Creative?] In-Mind Magazine.
* Fillion, R. (2009) ''Multicultural Dynamics and the Ends of History''. Ottawa: University of Ottawa Press, 2008.
* Gottfried, Paul Edward. (2002) "Multiculturalism and the Politics of Guilt:  Toward a Secular Theoracy," (University of Missouri).
*Grace Hui Chin Lin &amp; Patricia J. Larke (2007). The Chapter of Great Harmony in Confucianism
&lt;http://taiwanaggies.com/node/519&gt;
*Grace Hui Chin Lin &amp; Patricia J. Larke (2007). My Feelings toward Afrocentric Epistemology
&lt;http://taiwanaggies.com/node/517&gt;
*Icart, Jean-Claude. [http://nfb.ca/duneculturealautre/theme_article.php?id=2006&amp;pubid=18197 “Racism in Canada.” ''Across Cultures''.] Montreal: National Film Board of Canada, 2007.
*Jedwab, Jack. [http://nfb.ca/duneculturealautre/pdv_texte.php?id=2015 “The Diverse Family of Canadians: Documenting the Immigrant Experience in Canada.” ''Across Cultures''.] Montreal: National Film Board of Canada, 2007.
*[[Hans Köchler|Köchler, Hans]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=YI_nZjqwPIYC&amp;dq=%22Cultural+SElf-comprehension+of+Nations%22&amp;source=gbs_summary_s&amp;cad=0 ''Cultural Self-comprehension of Nations'']. Studies in International Cultural Relations, I. Tübingen/Basel: Erdmann, 1978.
*[[Hans Köchler|Köchler, Hans]]. "The Concept of the Nation and the Question of Nationalism. The Traditional 'Nation State' versus a Multicultural'Community State'," in: Michael Dunne and Tiziano Bonazzi (eds.), ''Citizenship and Rights in Multicultural Societies''. Keele: Keele University Press, 1995, pp.&amp;nbsp;44–51.
*Kukushkin, Vadim. [http://nfb.ca/duneculturealautre/theme_article.php?id=1994&amp;pubid=18018 “’Strangers Within Our Gates’: The Legacy of Intolerance.” ''Across Cultures''.] Montreal: National Film Board of Canada, 2007.
*Ortiz, Fernando. Cuban Counterpoint: Tobacco and Sugar, Durham, NC: Duke University Press,ISBN 0-8223-1616-1. Trans. Harriet de Onís.1995
*Pratt, Mary Lousis. "Arts of the Contact Zone." From Inquiry to Academic Writing: a Text and Reader. Boston: Bedford/St. Martin's, 2008. 355-68.
*Putnam, Robert D., "E Pluribus Unum: Diversity and Community in the Twenty-first Century -- The 2006 Johan Skytte Prize," ''Scandinavian Political Studies'' 30 (2), June 2007.
* [[John Russon|Russon, John]] (2003) ''Human Experience''. Albany: State University of New York Press, 2003.
* Sailer, Steve, [http://www.amconmag.com/article/2007/jan/15/00007/ "Fragmented Future: Multiculturalism doesn’t make vibrant communities but defensive ones,"] ''American Conservative'', Jan. 15, 2007.
*Salter, Frank, ''On Genetic Interests: Family, Ethnicity, and Humanity in an Age of Mass Migration'', 2007, ISBN 1 41280 596 1.

==External links==
*{{sep entry|multiculturalism|Multiculturalism|Sarah Song}}
*[http://archives.cbc.ca/society/celebrations/topics/3517/ CBC Digital Archives: Making The Mosaic: Multiculturalism in Canada]

[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Multiculturalism]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Sociology of culture]]

[[bg:Мултикултурализъм]]
[[ca:Multiculturalitat]]
[[cs:Multikulturalismus]]
[[cy:Amlddiwylliannaeth]]
[[de:Multikulturalismus]]
[[es:Multiculturalismo]]
[[eo:Multkulturismo]]
[[fr:Multiculturalisme]]
[[gl:Multiculturalismo]]
[[ko:다문화주의]]
[[hi:बहुसंस्कृतिवाद]]
[[id:Multikulturalisme]]
[[it:Multiculturalismo]]
[[he:רב-תרבותיות]]
[[kn:ಬಹುಸಾಂಸ್ಕೃತಿಕತೆ]]
[[lv:Multikulturālisms]]
[[hu:Multikulturalizmus]]
[[nl:Multiculturalisme]]
[[ja:多文化主義]]
[[no:Multikulturalisme]]
[[nn:Fleirkulturell]]
[[pl:Wielokulturowość]]
[[pt:Multiculturalismo]]
[[ru:Мультикультурализм]]
[[simple:Multiculturalism]]
[[fi:Monikulttuurisuus]]
[[sv:Mångkultur]]
[[ta:பல்லினப்பண்பாடு]]
[[uk:Мультикультуралізм]]
[[zh:多元文化政策]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>