<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041009193159|7230727" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="51885" pageid="51885" ns="0" title="Multiculturalism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-08T21:03:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Multiculturalism''' or '''cultural pluralism''' is a policy, ideal, or reality that emphasizes the unique characteristics of different cultures in the world, especially as they relate to one another in [[immigrant]] receiving nations.  The term was coined in [[Canada]] in the 1960s, but has since spread around the world. 

==Descriptive Multiculturalism==

Multiculturalism is a term often used to describe societies with a proliferation of different cultures.  Around the world wealthy countries have large numbers of immigrants with their own cultures and languages.  This multicultural reality has caused problems in some nations, but also has led to cultural exchanges that have benefited both groups.  For instance the introduction of the cuisine of the [[Indian subcontinent]] to the [[United Kingdom]] has revolutionized British eating.

The term "multicultural" can also be used to refer to localities in cities where people of different cultures co-exist. The actions of planners and those engaged in formulating public housing policy can result in some areas remaining monocultural, often due to pressure groups active in the local political arena. This term is especially current in the UK.

==Official Multiculturalism==

Multiculturalism can also be a prescriptive term which describes government policy.

In dealing with immigrants groups and their cultures, there are essentially three approaches-  
* [[Monoculturalism]]: In most [[Old World]] nations, culture is very closely linked to [[nationalism]], thus government policy is to assimilate immigrants. These countries have policies aiming at the social integration of immigrant groups to the national culture. This is typical of nations that define themselves as one and indivisible and do not recognize the existence of other nations within their midst.
* [[Melting Pot]]: In the [[United States]] the traditional view has been for a Melting Pot where all the immigrant cultures are mixed and amalgamated without state intervention. However, many states have different language policies within the union.
* Multiculturalism: a view that immigrants, and others, should preserve their cultures and the different cultures should interact peacefully within one nation. Today, this is the official policy of [[Canada]] and [[Australia]].

No country, both in past or present, has fully fallen into one of these categories. For example, France has made efforts to adapt French culture to new immigrant groups, while Canada still has many policies that work to encourage assimilation.

Others, such as [[Diane Ravitch]], use the term multiculturalism differently, describing both the Melting Pot, and Canada's Mosaic as being multicultural and refers to them as ''pluralistic'' and ''particularist'' multiculturalism. Pluralistic multiculturalism views each culture or subculture in a society as contributing unique and valuable cultural aspects to the whole culture. Particularist multiculturalism is more concerned with preserving the distinctions between cultures. 

===Origins===

The word grew out of [[Biculturalism]], which had long been Canada's official  policy to deal with the differences between the English-speaking majority and substantial French-speaking minority.  In the 1960s, the biculturalist view was challenged by groups as diverse as [[First Nations]] and [[China|Chinese]] immigrants and this counter opinion was termed "multiculturalist".  Under [[Pierre Trudeau]] in [[1971]], the nation moved to an official policy geared towards multiculturalism.  This policy has been supported by every subsequent government and was added to Canada's [[Canada Act|1982 constitution]].

===Implementation===

Around the world, important government multicultural policies can include:
*[[dual citizenship]]
*government support for [[newspaper]]s, [[television]], and [[radio]] in minority languages
*support for minority festivals, holidays, and celebrations
*acceptance of traditional and religious dress in schools, the military, and society in general
*support for arts from cultures around the world
*programs to encourage minority representation in politics, education, and the work force

While multiculturalist policies oppose cultural assimilation, countries such as Canada do support structural assimilation.  Immigrant groups are still encouraged to participate in the larger society, learn the majority languages, and enter the labour force.

=== Official Multiculturalism Around the World===

The other country to have most fully adopted Canada's view of multiculturalism is [[Australia]] where many of these policies related to multiculturalism are pursued, for example the formation of the [[Special Broadcasting Service]].

In the [[United States]] multiculturalism is not an official policy.  However, the government, in recent years, moved to support many multiculturalist policies.  In some ways, the United States has gone even further than Canada with such policies as [[gerrymandered]] districts to guarantee minority representation in government.

Like in the United States, the [[United Kingdom]] also does not have an official policy supporting multiculturalism, but does have a number of programmes with these goals.  

Multiculturalism, along with other [[identity politics]], has, in part, been so successful because it is a useful tool for politicians to win the votes of minority groups.  Government money for cultural celebrations or ethnic-specific newspapers can encourage new immigrants to support the governing party.

===Criticisms===

There have been many criticisms of official multiculturalism from both the left and right.  Criticizing the policies can be difficult, however, because they can quickly lead to accusations of [[racism]] and [[xenophobia]].

[[Diane Ravitch]] argues that the celebration of multicultural diversity in America is used to mask hostility toward the mainstream, as multiculturalists would claim that that mainstream has ignored [[black]]s, [[women]], [[American Indian]]s, and so on in history.

One of the dangers of pursuing multiculturist social policies is that social integration and cultural assimilation can be held back.  This can potentially encourage economic disparities and an exclusion of minority groups from mainstream politics. The political commentator [[Matthew Parris]] has questioned whether the pursuit of particularist multiculturalism is not [[apartheid]] by another name.

In Canada, the most noted Canadian critics of multiculturalism are [[Neil Bissoondath]] and [[Reginald Bibby]].  In his ''Selling Illusions: The Cult of Multiculturalism in Canada'', the [[Trinidad]] born Bissoondath argues that official multiculturalism limits the freedom of minority members by confining them to cultural and geographic ghettos.  He also argues that cultures are far too complex and must be transmitted through close family and kin relations.  To him, the government view of cultures as being about festivals and cuisine is a crude oversimplification that leads to easy stereotyping.

Bibby, in his ''Mosaic Madness: Pluralism Without a Cause'', argues that official multiculturalism is a divisive force that is reducing national solidarity and unity.

Another staunch critic of the use of the term "multiculturalism" by the government of Canada is the government of [[Quebec]], which, through its use of an interculturalism policy, seeks to integrate immigrants to the mainstream French-speaking society of Quebec. The government of Quebec understands pluralism as being a ''de facto'' feature of modern Quebec society or any other society that welcomes immigrants. Because it considers itself the national government of all Quebecers, the Quebec government seeks to have all its citizen participate to a common [[civic culture]]. In order to accomplish this, it promotes French, the language of the majority, as the common public language of all Quebecers. Whether as a first, second, or third language, French becomes the instrument which allows the [[socialization]] of Quebecers of all origins and forces interaction between them. Interculturalism is a policy that aims at fighting racism, misunderstanding of others, and ultimately bring about the [[solidarization]] of the [[multiethnic]] human [[collectivity]] the [[nation]] is supposed to be.

In the UK, Supporters of the government's approach have described it as having defended the rights of minorities to preserve their culture, while also seeking to ensure they become fully particpatory citizens - ie integrating without assimulating.  Critics say the policy fails on all accounts: If social conditions and racism become barriers to the integration of minorities, then multiculturalism does not properly function. There is now a lively debate in the UK over multiculturalism versus "social cohesion and inclusion", the current Labour government appearing to favour the latter.


==See also==

*[[Interculturalism]]
*[[Racial integration]]
*[[Transculturation]]
*[[Cosmopolitanism]]

==Links==
*[http://college.hmco.com/currentconflict/students/multicultural/ravitch_article/intro.html Multiculturalism: E Pluribus Plures] - article by [[Diane Ravitch]] on pluralistic vs. particularistic multiculturalism
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/3615379.stm News (10-Apr-2004): British Head of Commission for Racial Equality says the term should be scrapped]
[[de:Multikulturalismus]]
*[http://www.opendemocracy.net/debates/issue-1-111.jsp Commentary and user comments] from ''Open Democracy - Multiculturalism: translating difference''</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>