<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091114091448|325769969" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="51885" pageid="51885" ns="0" title="Multiculturalism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-14T11:22:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=September 2009}}
{{Unbalanced|date=September 2009}}

'''Multiculturalism''' is the acceptance of multiple [[ethnic]] [[culture|cultures]], for practical reasons and/or for the sake of [[diversity (politics)|diversity]] and applied to the [[demographics|demographic make-up]] of a specific place, usually at the organizational level, e.g. [[school]]s, [[business]]es, [[neighborhood]]s, [[city|cities]] or [[nation]]s. In this context, multiculturalists advocate extending equitable status to distinct ethnic and [[religion|religious]] groups without promoting any specific ethnic, religious, and/or cultural community values as central. 

The policy of multiculturalism is often contrasted with the concepts [[cultural assimilation|assimilationism]] and [[social integration]]. Multicultural policies are sometimes confused with the concept of the ''[[multinational state]]''. A country may be multi-national without being multicultural.

Some countries have official (or ''[[de jure]]'') [[policy|policies]] of multiculturalism aimed at promoting social cohesion by recognizing distinct groups within a [[society]] and allowing those groups to celebrate and maintain their [[culture]]s or cultural identities. Many critics of deliberated, government-instituted policies believe they artificially perpetuate social divisions, damaging the [[social cohesion]] of the [[nation-state]]. 

However, proponents of multicultural programs argue that social cohesion has too often been achieved either by explicit discrimination against cultural minority groups (e.g., laws that restrict the freedoms of certain groups) or by an implicit discrimination which rejects other cultural forms as being without value (e.g., school programs that never teach the historic and artistic contributions of minorities). 

Critics of multiculturalism often charge multiculturalists with practicing [[cultural relativism]] (i.e., judging customs and practices of other cultures in their contexts), often confusing this with [[moral relativism]] (lack of an idea of right and wrong), and they emphasize that not all cultural values and practices must be held in equal regard in every given society. They warn against special treatment that might violate the principal of [[equality before the law]], and emphasize that [[citizenship]] denotes an tacit agreement to abide by the laws, customs and accepted [[value system]] of nation, ''especially'' in regards to those who chose to emigrate from abroad to join their newly adopted society. 

Advocates of multiculturalism counter these objections by claiming that 1) the issue is not cultural relativism but the whitewashing of history, i.e., that history has been written to play up the contributions of the dominant group and to downplay the (often significant) contributions of minority groups; 2) with regards to cultural/artistic contributions, the claim that minority culture is inferior is often based less on aesthetic quality than on politically-motivated criteria; 3) the issue is often not legal equality but simply recognition that minorities do exist in the culture; and 4) many minority groups did not immigrate but were either imported or previously living on the land.

==Support for multiculturalism==
Multiculturalism is seen by its supporters as a fairer system that allows people to truly express who they are within a society, that is more tolerant and that adapts better to social issues. They argue that in societies where ethnic groups have comparatively equal status, difference is tolerated better,{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} e.g. Sweden, which has low income inequality.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} They also argue that multiculturalism is a better system because culture is always changing. For instance, the culture of the United Kingdom has not arisen from one ethnic group, but from the 'immigration' and influence of Anglo-Saxons (''[[Anglo-Saxon invasion of Britain]]''), Vikings (''[[Great Heathen Army]]''), Normans (''[[Norman conquest of England]]'') and so on. Therefore, they argue, culture is not one definable thing based on one race or religion, but is the result of multiple factors that change as the world changes.

==Opposition to multiculturalism==
{{Main|Criticism of multiculturalism}}
Criticism of [[multiculturalism]] often debates whether the multicultural ideal of benignly co-existing cultures that interrelate and influence one another, and yet remain distinct, is sustainable, paradoxical or even desirable. [[Nation states]] that, in the case of many European nations, would previously have been synonymous with a distinctive cultural identity of their own, lose out to enforced multiculturalism and that this ultimately erodes the host nations distinct culture&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/0000000CA4C4.htm spiked-culture | Article | Backlash against multiculturalism?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/00000002D35E.htm spiked-politics | Article | The trouble with multiculturalism&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4295318.stm Report attacks multiculturalism]&lt;/ref&gt;. 

Other critics argue that multiculturalism leads directly to restrictions in the rights and freedoms for certain groups and that as such, it is bad for democracy, undemocratic and against universal human rights. For instance, [[Susan Moller Okin]] wrote about this question in her essay "Is Multiculturalism Bad for Women?" (1999).&lt;ref&gt;Okin, [http://www.bostonreview.net/BR22.5/okin.html "Is Multiculturalism Bad for Women?"], ''Boston Review'' 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Multiculturalism in contemporary Western society==
[[Image:Outside Union Station.jpg|thumb|upright|''Monument to Multiculturalism'' by Francesco Pirelli in [[Toronto]], [[Canada]]. Four identical sculptures are located in [[Buffalo City Local Municipality|Buffalo City]], [[South Africa]]; [[Changchun]], [[China]]; [[Sarajevo]], [[Bosnia]] and [[Sydney]], [[Australia]].]]
Multiculturalism was adopted as official policy, in several [[Western world|Western]] nations from the 1970s onward, for reasons that varied from country to country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unesco.org/most/pp4.htm Policy Paper no. 4 - Multiculturalism: New Policy Responses to Diversity]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pch.gc.ca/progs/multi/reports/ann01-2002/part1_e.cfm Multiculturalism ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www4.gu.edu.au/ext/civics/cv02/mod03/cv02m03t02.htm Immigration and Multiculturalism]&lt;/ref&gt; The great cities of the Western world are increasingly made of a mosaic of
cultures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unu.edu/dialogue/papers/claval-s2.pdf Multiculturalism and the Dynamics of Modern Civilizations]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Government multicultural policies may include:{{cn|date=November 2009}}
*recognition of [[multiple citizenship]] (the multiple citizenship itself usually results from the [[nationality law]]s of another country)
*government support for [[newspaper]]s, [[television]], and [[radio]] in [[minority language]]s
*support for minority festivals, holidays, and celebrations
*acceptance of traditional and religious dress in schools, the military, and society in general
*support for music and arts from minority cultures
*programs to encourage minority representation in politics, SET (Science, Engineering and Technology), Mathematics, education, and the work force in general.
*enforcement of different codes of law on members of each ethnic group (e.g. [[Malaysia]] enforces [[Shari'a]] law, but only for a particular ethnic group)

===Multiculturalism as introductory to monoculturalism===
[[Image:Hk anti-discrimination poster.jpg|thumb|right|250px|An anti-discrimination poster in a [[Hong Kong]] [[MTR|subway]] station. Circa. 2005]]
Multiculturalism, as generally understood, refers to a theoretical approach and a number of policies adopted in Western [[nation-state]]s, which had seemingly achieved a de facto single national identity during the 18th and/or 19th centuries. Many nation-states in Africa, Asia, and the Americas are culturally diverse, and are 'multi-cultural' in a [[descriptive]] sense. In some, [[communalism]] is a major political issue. The policies adopted by these states  often have parallels with multicultural-ist policies in the [[Western world]], but the historical background is different, and the goal may be a mono-cultural or mono-ethnic [[nation-building]] - for instance in the Malaysian governments attempt to create a 'Malaysian race' by 2020.&lt;ref&gt;[[The Economist]]: ''[http://www.economist.com/surveys/displayStory.cfm?story_id=1677228 The changing of the guard]'', April 3rd 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Origins in Canada===
{{Main|Multiculturalism in Canada}}
[[Image:German immigrants, Quebec City, Canada, 1911.jpg|thumb|left|German immigrants in [[Quebec City]] in 1911]]
Canada has the [[Immigration to Canada#Immigration rate|highest per capita immigration rate in the world]],&lt;ref name="highest immigration"&gt;{{cite web |author=Benjamin Dolin and Margaret Young, Law and Government Division |publisher=Library of Parliament |url=http://www.parl.gc.ca/information/library/PRBpubs/bp190-e.htm  
|title=Canada's Immigration Program |date=2004-10-31|accessdate=2006-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; driven by [[Economic impact of immigration to Canada|economic policy]] and [[Immigration to Canada#Immigration categories|family reunification]]. In 2001, 250,640 people immigrated to Canada. Newcomers settle mostly in the major urban areas of [[Toronto]], [[Vancouver]] and [[Montreal]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canadastatistics.info/canadian-people.html Canadian People - Learn About Canada's People], CanadaStatistics.info&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1990s and 2000s, the largest component of Canada’s immigrants came from [[Asia]], including the Middle East, South Asia, South-East Asia and East Asia.&lt;ref name = "migrate-Inflow"&gt;[http://www.migrationinformation.org/datahub/countrydata/country.cfm Inflow of foreign-born population by country of birth, by year]&lt;/ref&gt; Canadian society is often depicted as being very progressive, diverse, and [[multicultural]]. Accusing a person of racism in Canada is usually considered a serious slur.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last = Fontaine|first = Phil|author-link = Phil Fontaine|url = http://www.queensu.ca/sps/conferences_events/lectures/donald_gow/98lecture.pdf|format=PDF|title = Modern Racism in Canada by Phil Fontaine|place = Queen's University|date = April 24, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; All political parties are now cautious about criticizing of the high level of immigration, because, as noted by the [[Globe and Mail]], "in the early 1990s, the old [[Reform Party of Canada|Reform Party]] was branded 'racist' for suggesting that immigration levels be lowered from 250,000 to 150,000."&lt;ref name=Globevolpe&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/Page/document/v4/sub/MarketingPage?user_URL=http://www.theglobeandmail.com%2Fservlet%2Fstory%2FRTGAM.20051212.wxsmart12%2FBNStory%2FspecialDecision2006%2F&amp;ord=1155737424463&amp;brand=theglobeandmail&amp;force_login=true Is the current model of immigration the best one for Canada?], [[Globe and Mail]], 12 December 2005, URL accessed 16 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Canflagcartoon.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Political cartoon on Canada's multicultural identity, from 1911]]

===Argentina===
{{Main|Demographics of Argentina}}
Though not called ''Multiculturalism'' as such, the [[Constitution of Argentina#Preamble|preamble]] of Argentina's constitution explicitly promotes [[Immigration to Argentina|immigration]], and recognizes the individual's [[multiple citizenship]] from other countries. Though 86% of Argentina's population self-identify as of [[European ethnic groups|European descent]]&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;[http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Argentina.html Argentina]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="CIA"&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/print/ar.html CIA - The World Factbook - Argentina]&lt;/ref&gt;  to this day a high level of multiculturalism remains a feature of the [[Argentine Culture|Argentine's culture]],&lt;ref&gt;,
[http://www.argentina.ar/_en/culture/ Argentine Culture Rich and Diverse]&lt;/ref&gt; allowing foreign festivals and holidays (e.g. [[Saint Patrick's Day]]), supporting all kinds of art or cultural expression from minorities, as well as their diffusion through an important multicultural presence in the media; for instance it is not uncommon to find newspapers&lt;ref&gt;*[http://www.buenosairesherald.com/ Buenos Aires Herald, Argentine-English language newspaper]&lt;/ref&gt; or radios program in English, German, Italian or [[Guarani language]] in Argentina.

===Australia===
{{Main|Multiculturalism in Australia}}
The other country to have most fully adopted Canadian-style multiculturalism is Australia, with many similar policies, for example the formation of the [[Special Broadcasting Service]]. While the [[White Australia Policy]] was quietly dismantled after World War II by various changes to [[Immigration to Australia|immigration policy]], the full political introduction of official policies of multiculturalism was not until 1973. The idea of multiculturalism especially became popular in Australia during the 1980s. It replaced the notion of [[cultural assimilation|assimilation]] where non-British migrants were expected to change their way of life and abandon their cultural traditions to fit in with existing Australian traditions. Organizations were formed to encourage immigrants to keep aspects of their original culture, and to share them with other Australians.

===United States===
In the United States, multiculturalism is not clearly established in policy at the federal level.

[[Image:Mulberry Street NYC c1900 LOC 3g04637u edit.jpg|thumb|Mulberry Street, along which Manhattan's [[Little Italy, Manhattan|Little Italy]] is centered. [[Lower East Side, Manhattan|Lower East Side]], circa 1900.]]
In the United States, continuous mass immigration had been a feature of economy and society since the first half of the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hasia Diner]], [http://usinfo.state.gov/journals/itsv/0208/ijse/diner.htm "Immigration and U.S. History"], ''eJournal USA'', February 2008{{Dead link|date=September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The absorption of the stream of immigrants became, in itself, a prominent feature of America's [[national myth]]. The idea of the [[Melting pot]] is a [[metaphor]] that implies that all the immigrant cultures are mixed and amalgamated without state intervention.&lt;ref&gt;Zangwil, Israel. ''The Melting Pot,'' 1908.&lt;/ref&gt; The Melting Pot implied that each individual immigrant, and each group of immigrants, assimilated into American society at their own pace. An Americanized (and often stereotypical) version of the original nation's cuisine, and its holidays, survived.
Note that the Melting Pot tradition co-exists with a belief in national unity, dating from the [[Founding Fathers of the United States|American founding fathers]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
"Providence has been pleased to give this one connected country to one united people — a people descended from the same ancestors, speaking the same language, professing the same religion, attached to the same principles of government, very similar in their manners and customs... This country and this people seem to have been made for each other, and it appears as if it was the design of Providence, that an inheritance so proper and convenient for a band of brethren, united to each other by the strongest ties, should never be split into a number of unsocial, jealous, and alien sovereignties."&lt;ref&gt;[[John Jay]], ''First American Supreme Court Chief Justice'',[[Federalist No. 2|Federalist Paper No. 2]]'''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

As a [[philosophy]], multiculturalism began as part of the [[pragmatism]] movement at the end of the nineteenth century in [[Europe]] and the United States, then as political and cultural [[pluralism]] at the turn of the twentieth. It was partly in response to a new wave of European imperialism in sub-Saharan Africa and the massive immigration of Southern and Eastern Europeans to the United States and [[Latin America]]. Philosophers, psychologists and historians and early sociologists such as [[Charles Sanders Peirce]], [[William James]], [[George Santayana]], [[Horace Kallen]], [[John Dewey]], [[W. E. B. Du Bois]] and [[Alain Locke]] developed concepts of [[cultural pluralism]], from which emerged what we understand today as multiculturalism. In ''Pluralistic Universe'' (1909), William James espoused the idea of a "plural society."  James saw pluralism as "crucial to the formation of philosophical and social [[humanism]] to help build a better, more egalitarian society.&lt;ref name = Boening&gt;{{cite news 
  | last =Boening 
  | first =Astrid B. 
  | coauthors = 
  | title =Euro-Islam – A Constructivist Idea or a Concept of the English School?
  | newspaper =European Union Miami Analysis (EUMA)
  | location =
  | volume =4
  | issue =12
  | pages =3-10
  | publisher =Miami-Florida European Union Center of Excellence
  | date =May 2007 
  | url =http://www.miami.edu/eucenter/Boening_EuroIslam_EUMA2007edi.pdf
  | format =pdf 
  | accessdate =30 September 2009 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
Multicultural policies were adopted by local administrations from the 1970s and 1980s onwards, in particular, by the Labour government of [[Tony Blair]]{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}  In national policy, legislation includes  ''Race Relations Act''  and the ''British Nationality Act'' of 1948. 
Most of the immigrants of the last decades came from the [[Indian subcontinent]] or the [[Caribbean]], i.e. from former [[British overseas territories|British colonies]]. In 2004 the number of people who became British citizens rose to a record 140,795 — a rise of 12% on the previous year. This number had risen dramatically since 2000. The overwhelming majority of new citizens come from Africa (32%) and Asia (40%), the largest three groups being people from [[Pakistan]], [[India]] and [[Somalia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4706862.stm BBC Thousands in UK citizenship queue]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Western world|Western]] English-speaking countries, multiculturalism as an official national policy started in Canada in 1971, followed by Australia in 1973.&lt;ref name = Bissoondath&gt;Bissoondath, Neil. 2002.  ''Selling Illusions: The Myth of Multiculturalism''. Toronto: Penguin. ISBN 9780141006765.&lt;/ref&gt; It was quickly adopted as official policy by most member-states of the [[European Union]].  Recently, right-of-center governments in several European states—notably the [[Netherlands]] and [[Denmark]]— have reversed the national policy and returned to an official monoculturalism.&lt;ref name = Bissoondath /&gt; A similar reversal is the subject of debate in the United Kingdom, among others, due to evidence of incipient segregation and anxieties over "home-grown" [[terrorism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.workpermit.com/news/2005_04_26/uk/uk_immigration_debate.htm Fact or fiction in the great UK immigration debate]. workpermit.com. News. April 26, 2005. Retrieved on: October 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Continental Europe===
[[Image:Austria Hungary ethnic.svg|thumb|Ethno-linguistic map of [[Austria–Hungary]], 1910.]]
Historically, Europe has always been polycultural--a mixture of Latin, Germanic and Celtic cultures influenced by the importation of Hebraic, Hellenic and even Muslim belief systems; although the continent was supposedly unified by the super-position of Roman Catholic Christianity, it is accepted that geographic and cultural differences continued from antiquity into the modern age.

Especially in the 19th century, the ideology of [[nationalism]] transformed the way Europeans thought about the [[Sovereign state|state]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} Existing states were broken up and new ones created; the new [[nation-states]] were founded on the principle that each [[nation]] is entitled to its own [[sovereignty|sovereign]] state and to engender, protect, and preserve its own unique culture and history. Unity, under this ideology, is seen as an essential feature of the nation and the nation-state - unity of descent, unity of culture, unity of language, and often unity of religion. The nation-state constitutes a culturally [[wiktionary:Homogeneity|homogeneous]] society, although some national movements recognized regional differences.

Where cultural unity was insufficient, it was encouraged and enforced by the state. The 19th-century nation-states developed an array of policies - the most important was compulsory [[primary education]] in the [[national language]]. The language itself was often standardized by a linguistic academy, and regional languages were ignored or suppressed. Some nation-states pursued violent policies of [[cultural assimilation]] and even [[ethnic cleansing]].

Some European Union countries have introduced policies for "social cohesion", "integration", and (sometimes) "assimilation". They are sometimes a direct reversal of earlier multiculturalist policies, and seek to assimilate immigrant minorities and restore a ''[[de facto]]'' mono-cultural society.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} The policies include:
*compulsory courses and/or tests on [[historiography and nationalism|national history]], on the [[constitution]] and the [[legal system]] (e.g., the computer-based test for individuals seeking naturalization in the UK named [[Life in the United Kingdom test]])
*introduction of an official national history, such as the national [[Western canon|canon]] defined for the Netherlands by the [[Frits van Oostrom|van Oostrom]] Commission,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.entoen.nu/ Official Web site]&lt;/ref&gt; and promotion of that history (e.g., by exhibitions about [[national hero]]es)
*tests designed to elicit "unacceptable" values. In [[Baden-Württemberg]] immigrants are asked what they would do if their son says he is a [[Homosexuality|homosexual]]. (The expected answer is that they would accept it).&lt;ref&gt;BBC report at [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4655240.stm], full list of questions in German at taz, [http://www.taz.de/index.php?id=archivseite&amp;dig=2006/01/04/a0154]&lt;/ref&gt;
*prohibitions on [[hijab|Islamic dress]] — especially the [[niqab]] (often misnamed as [[burqa]]).&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/nov/11/religion.uk Netherlands moves toward total ban on Muslim veils]'', Guardian,  November 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Netherlands===
{{Main|Multiculturalism in the Netherlands}}
In the 1950s, the [[Netherlands]] was generally a mono-ethnic and monocultural society: it was not explicitly [[monolingualism|monolingual]], but almost everyone could speak standard [[Dutch language|Dutch]]; [[Frisian]] and [[Nedersaksisch]] were the only indigenous minority languages. Its inhabitants shared a classic national identity, with a national [[mythos]] emphasizing the [[Dutch Golden Age]], and national heroes such as Admiral [[Michiel de Ruyter]]. Dutch society was segmented along religious and ideological lines, sometimes coinciding with differences in social class and lifestyle. This segmentation had developed since the late 19th century into a uniquely Dutch version, called [[pillarization]], enabling peaceful cooperation between the leaders of the various "pillars", while their constituencies remained largely segregated.

===Russia===
{{Refimprove|date=November 2009}}
Because of colonialism and the gradual accretion of land over several centuries, Russia has over 150 different ethnic groups. Russia is the only Western power that has managed to keep a significant amount of its colonial territory to this day. The Caucasus, which has cost the Russian Empire more to contain than the British Raj cost for the British Empire, continues to be a hotbed of conflict to this day.

===Belgium===
In this field, Belgium shows the huge differences between multiculturalism and [[interculturalism]]. In the Flemish part, [[Flanders]], the official policy (which is supported by all main political parties except for one extreme-right party) is clearly inter-culturalist. The French-speaking parties however are very much multiculturalist.

==Multiculturalism in contemporary Eastern societies==

===India===
According to many scholars, [[India]] is the most culturally, linguistically and genetically diverse geographical entity after the African continent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/profiles/India.pdf India, a Country Study] ''United States Library of Congress, Note on Ethnic groups''&lt;/ref&gt; India's democratic republic is "premised on a national belief in pluralism, not the standard nationalist invocation of a shared history, a single language and an assimilationist culture."&lt;ref&gt;"[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6943598.stm India's model democracy]," BBC.&lt;/ref&gt; State boundaries in India are mostly drawn on linguistic lines.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commonlii.org/in/legis/num_act/sra1956250/ States Reorganization Act 1956]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition India is the most religiously diverse country in the world, with significant [[Hindu]] (80.5%) , [[Muslim]] (13.4%), [[Christian]] (2.3%), [[Sikh]] (2.1%), [[Buddhist]], [[Bahá'í Faith in India|Bahá'í]], [[Ahmadiyya Muslim Community|Ahmadi]], [[Jain]] and [[Parsi people|Parsi]] populations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.censusindia.gov.in/ Indian Census]&lt;/ref&gt; Occasionally, however, India has encountered [[Religious violence in India|religiously motivated violence]], &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog/NUSCLA.html Democracy, Religious Violence, and India's Future]. Martha C. Nussbaum. ''Harvard University Press.''&lt;/ref&gt; such as the [[Moplah Riots]], the [[Bombay riots]], the [[1984 anti-Sikh riots]] and [[2002 Gujarat riots]].

===Indonesia===
There are more than 700 living languages  spoken in Indonesia&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ethnologue.com/show_country.asp?name=indonesia Ethnologue report for Indonesia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and although predominantly Muslim the country also has large Christian and Hindu populations. Indonesia's national motto, "Bhinneka tunggal ika" ("Unity in Diversity" lit. "many, yet one"), articulates the diversity that shapes the country. Due to migration within Indonesia (as part of government [[transmigration program]]s or otherwise), there are significant populations of ethnic groups who reside outside of their traditional regions. Soon after [[Abdurrahman Wahid]] came into power in 1999, he quickly abolished some of the discriminatory laws in efforts to improve race relationships. [[Chinese Indonesian]]s are now in the era of rediscovery. Many younger generations, who cannot speak Mandarin due to the ban decades earlier, choose to learn Mandarin, as many learning centers open throughout the country. The [[Ambon, Maluku]] was the site of some of the worst violence between Christian and Muslim groups that gripped the [[Maluku Islands]] between 1999 and 2002.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/2243896.stm Religious violence erupts in Moluccas], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;

===Malaysia===
{{Main|Ketuanan Melayu}}
[[Malaysia]] is a multiethnic country, with [[Malay (ethnic group)|Malays]] making up the majority, close to 52% of the population. About 30% of the population are [[Chinese Malaysian|Malaysians of Chinese descent]]. [[Indian Malaysian|Malaysians of Indian descent]] comprise about 8% of the population. The remaining 10% comprises:
* native [[East Malaysia]]ns, namely [[Bajau]], [[Bidayuh]], [[Dusun]], [[Iban]], [[Kadazan]], [[Melanau]], [[Orang Ulu]], [[Sarawakian Malay]]s, etc. 
* other native tribes of [[Peninsular Malaysia]], such as the [[Orang Asli]] and Siamese people, and 
* non-native tribes of Peninsular Malaysia such as the [[Chettiar]]s, the [[Peranakan]] and the Portuguese. 

The [[Malaysian New Economic Policy]] or NEP serves as a form of affirmative action (see [[Bumiputera (Malaysia)|Bumiputera]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/6237328.stm Malaysia fury at EU envoy remarks], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt; It promotes structural changes in various aspects of life from education to economic to social integration. Established after the [[May 13 Incident|May 13 racial riots]] of 1969, it sought to address the significant imbalance in the economic sphere where the minority [[Han Chinese|Chinese]] population had substantial control over commercial activity in the country.

The [[Malay Peninsula]] has a long history of international trade contacts, influencing its ethnic and religious composition. Predominantly [[Malays (ethnic group)|Malays]] before the 18th century, the ethnic composition changed dramatically when the British introduced new industries, and imported Chinese and Indian labor. Several regions in the then [[British Malaya]] such as [[Penang]], [[Malacca]] and [[Singapore]] became Chinese dominated. Co-existence between the three ethnicities (and other minor groups) was largely peaceful, despite the fact the immigration affected the demographic and cultural position of the Malays.

Preceding independence of the [[Federation of Malaya]], a [[social contract (Malaysia)|social contract]] was negotiated as the basis of a new society. The contract as reflected in the [[Constitution of Malaysia|1957 Malayan Constitution and the 1963 Malaysian Constitution]] states that the immigrant groups are granted citizenship, and Malays' special rights are guaranteed. This is often referred to the [[Bumiputra]] policy.

These [[Pluralism (political philosophy)|pluralist]] policies have come under pressure from orthodox Muslims and [[Islamism|Islamist]] parties, who oppose secular and non-Islamic religious influences. The issue is related to the controversial [[status of religious freedom in Malaysia]].

===Mauritius===
Multiculturalism is a characteristic feature of the island of [[Mauritius]]. Mauritian society includes people from many different ethnic and religious groups: Hindu, Muslim and Sikh [[Indo-Mauritian]]s, [[Mauritian Creole people|Mauritian Creoles]] (of African and [[Malagasy people|Malagasy]] descent), Buddhist and Roman Catholic [[Sino-Mauritian]]s and [[Franco-Mauritian]]s (descendants of the original [[French people|French]] colonists).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infomauritius.com/ Some facts about Mauritius]&lt;/ref&gt; 

===The Philippines===
The [[Philippines]] is the 8th most multiethnic nation in the world.&lt;ref&gt;The [[Philippines]] ranks 8th among 240 countries in terms of ethnic diversity. YEOH Kok Kheng, ''[http://www.fep.um.edu.my/working%20papers/2001/FEA-WP-2001-003.pdf Towards an Index of Ethnic Fractionalization]'', Table 1.&lt;/ref&gt; It has 10 distinct major indigenous ethnic groups mainly the [[Bicolano people|Bicolano]], [[Ibanag people|Ibanag]], [[Ilocano people|Ilocano]], [[Ivatan people|Ivatan]], [[Kapampangan people|Kapampangan]], [[Moro (ethnic group)|Moro]], [[Pangasinense people|Pangasinense]], [[Sambal people|Sambal]], [[Tagalog people|Tagalog]] and [[Visayan people|Visayan]]. The Philippines also has several aboriginal races such as the [[Bajau|Badjao]], [[Igorot]], [[Lumad]], [[Mangyan]] and [[Negritos]]. The country also has considerable communities of [[American settlement in the Philippines|American]], [[Arab settlement in the Philippines|Arabic]], [[Chinese Filipinos|Chinese]], [[Hinduism in the Philippines|Indian]] and [[Filipinos of Spanish descent|Hispanic]] descent and many more. The Philippine government has various programs supporting and preserving the nation's ethnic diversity.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2794.htm&lt;/ref&gt;


===Singapore===
Singapore recognizes three other languages, namely, [[Mandarin Chinese]], [[Tamil language|Tamil]] and [[Malay language|Malay]] as its official languages, with [[English language|English]] being the national language. Besides being a [[multilingualism|multilingual]] country, Singapore also acknowledges festivals celebrated by these three ethnic communities.

Areas which are enclaves containing a large population of certain ethnic groups exist in areas such as [[Chinatown, Singapore|Chinatown]], [[Geylang]] and [[Little India, Singapore|Little India]] in Singapore.

==See also==
{{div col|cols=3}}
* [[Before Columbus Foundation]]
* [[Ethnic origin]]
* [[Ethnocentrism]]
* [[Cosmopolitanism]]
* [[Cultural competence]]
* [[Cross-culturalism]]
*[[Cultural Marxism]]
* [[Cultural mosaic]]
* [[Cultural pluralism]]
* [[Global Centre for Pluralism]] (Canada)
* [[Global justice]]
* [[Interculturalism]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Miscegenation]]
* ''[[Multiculturalism without Culture]]'' (book)
* [[Multikulti]]
* [[Multinational state]]
* [[Nation-building]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Plural society]]
* [[Political correctness]]
* [[Psi Sigma Phi]] Multicultural Fraternity, Incorporated
* [[Racial integration]]
* [[Racialism]]
* [[Societalism]]
* Society for the Study of [[Multi-Ethnic Literature of the United States]] (MELUS)
* [[Teaching for social justice]]
* [[Transculturation]]
* ''[[Unrooted Childhoods: Memoirs of Growing up Global]]'' (book)
* [[White guilt]]
* [[Whiteness studies]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{refs|3}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last= Ankerl |first= Guy |title= Global communication without universal civilization (Coexisting contemporary civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western) |origyear= 2000 |series= INU societal research |volume= 1|publisher= INU Press |location= Geneva |isbn= 2-88155-004-5 |pages=|year= 2000 }}
* Ankerl, Guy. ''Coexisting Contemporary Civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western''. INU Press, Geneva 2000, ISBN 2 88155 004 5 .
* Ellis, Frank . [http://www.amren.com/mtnews/archives/2009/05/multiculturalis.php Multiculturalism and Marxism] American Renaissance, November 1999
* Barzilai, Gad. (2003). ''Communities and Law: Politics and Cultures of Legal Identities.'' (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press).
* Chiu, C.-Y. &amp; Lueng, A. (2007). [http://www.in-mind.org/special-issue/do-multicultural-experiences-make-people-more-creative-if-so-2.html Do Multicultural Experiences Make People More Creative?] In-Mind Magazine.
* Fillion, R. (2009) ''Multicultural Dynamics and the Ends of History''. Ottawa: University of Ottawa Press, 2008.
* Gottfried, Paul Edward. (2002) "Multiculturalism and the Politics of Guilt:  Toward a Secular Theoracy," (University of Missouri).
*Icart, Jean-Claude. [http://nfb.ca/duneculturealautre/theme_article.php?id=2006&amp;pubid=18197 “Racism in Canada.” ''Across Cultures''.] Montreal: National Film Board of Canada, 2007.
*Jedwab, Jack. [http://nfb.ca/duneculturealautre/pdv_texte.php?id=2015 “The Diverse Family of Canadians: Documenting the Immigrant Experience in Canada.” ''Across Cultures''.] Montreal: National Film Board of Canada, 2007.
*[[Hans Köchler|Köchler, Hans]]. [http://books.google.com/books?id=YI_nZjqwPIYC&amp;dq=%22Cultural+SElf-comprehension+of+Nations%22&amp;source=gbs_summary_s&amp;cad=0 ''Cultural Self-comprehension of Nations'']. Studies in International Cultural Relations, I. Tübingen/Basel: Erdmann, 1978.
*[[Hans Köchler|Köchler, Hans]]. "The Concept of the Nation and the Question of Nationalism. The Traditional 'Nation State' versus a Multicultural'Community State'," in: Michael Dunne and Tiziano Bonazzi (eds.), ''Citizenship and Rights in Multicultural Societies''. Keele: Keele University Press, 1995, pp.&amp;nbsp;44–51. 
*Kukushkin, Vadim. [http://nfb.ca/duneculturealautre/theme_article.php?id=1994&amp;pubid=18018 “’Strangers Within Our Gates’: The Legacy of Intolerance.” ''Across Cultures''.] Montreal: National Film Board of Canada, 2007.
* [[John Russon|Russon, John]] (2003) ''Human Experience''. Albany: State University of New York Press, 2003.

==External links==
*[http://archives.cbc.ca/society/celebrations/topics/3517/ CBC Digital Archives: Making The Mosaic: Multiculturalism in Canada]

[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Multiculturalism]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Sociology of culture]]

[[bg:Мултикултурализъм]]
[[ca:Multiculturalitat]]
[[cs:Multikulturalismus]]
[[de:Multikulturalismus]]
[[es:Multiculturalismo]]
[[eo:Multkulturismo]]
[[fr:Multiculturalisme]]
[[gl:Multiculturalismo]]
[[ko:다문화주의]]
[[id:Multikulturalisme]]
[[it:Multiculturalismo]]
[[he:רב-תרבותיות]]
[[lv:Multikulturālisms]]
[[hu:Multikulturalizmus]]
[[nl:Multiculturalisme]]
[[ja:多文化主義]]
[[no:Multikulturalisme]]
[[nn:Fleirkulturell]]
[[pl:Wielokulturowość]]
[[pt:Multiculturalismo]]
[[ru:Мультикультурализм]]
[[simple:Multiculturalism]]
[[fi:Monikulttuurisuus]]
[[sv:Mångkultur]]
[[ta:பல்லினப்பண்பாடு]]
[[zh:多元文化政策]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>