<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031004000131|1521794" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="51885" pageid="51885" ns="0" title="Multiculturalism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-04T00:01:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Multikulturalismus]]

'''Multiculturalism''' emphasizes the unique characteristics of mulitplicity of cultures in the world, especially as the relate to one another in America. 

[[Diane Ravitch]] identifies the two main currents of multiculturalism as ''pluralistic'' and ''particularist''. Pluralistic multiculturalism views each culture or subculture in a society as contributing unique and valuable cultural aspects to the whole culture ("melting pot"). Particularist multiculturalism is more concerned with preserving the distinctions between cultures. 

Particularists often deride Western Christendom in general or specifically America as narrowly "Eurocentric". For example, [[Edward Said]]'s book ''[[Orientalism]]'' claims Westerners are inherently incapable of understanding [[Islam]].

It is often difficult to distinguish the two currents Ravitch describes, as the celebration of a "diversity" can mask a hostility toward a mainstream which has ignored blacks, women, American Indians and so on in American history.

==Links==
*[http://college.hmco.com/currentconflict/students/multicultural/ravitch_article/intro.html Multiculturalism: E Pluribus Plures] - article by [[Diane Ravitch]] on pluralistic vs. particularistic multiculturalism</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>