<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061111232916|87228989" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="145439" pageid="145439" ns="0" title="Women&#039;s rights"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-11T23:29:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup-date|June 2006}}

{{rights}}
The term '''Women’s rights''' typically refers to [[Freedom (political)|freedoms]] inherently possessed by women and girls of all ages, which may be institutionalized or illegitimately suppressed by law or custom in a particular society.  These liberties are grouped together and differentiated from broader notions of [[human rights]] because they often differ from the freedoms inherently possessed and/or recognized by men and boys, and because activism surrounds this issue claims an inherent historical and traditional bias against the exercise of rights by women.  These differences are at least partially socially constructed rather than biologically immutable conditions.  See articles about [[women]], the term some feminists see as a "gender unbiased term."

Issues commonly associated with notions of women's rights include, though are not limited to:


{{weasel words}}


*rights to bodily integrity and autonomy
*the right to [[suffrage|vote]]
*the right to hold public office 
*the right to work
*the right to [[equal pay|fair wages]]
*the right to own [[property]]
*the right to [[education]]
*[[marriage|marital]] rights
*[[parenting|parental]] rights
*[[religious]] rights
*the right to serve in the [[military]]
*the right to enter into legal [[contracts]]

==Connections to feminism==
{{Feminism}}
Notions of women’s rights are closely connected to [[feminism]].  Feminist movements usually call for greater acknowledgment of women’s rights but may also connote a focus on [[philosophy]] and [[social theory|theory]] not necessarily associated with more utilitarian women’s right movements directed at specific reforms.

==Notable women’s rights activists==
* [[Guru Nanak]] (1469-1539) The founder of [[Sikhism]] also promoted [[Women in Sikhism|equal rights for Women]]
*[[Qasim Amin]] (1863-1908) - [[Egypt|Egyptian]] jurist, early advocate of women’s rights in [[Islam|Islamic]] society
*[[Susan B. Anthony]] (1820-1906) - [[United States|American]] civil rights leader and suffragette, co-founder of the [[National Woman's Suffrage Association]], tried for casting a vote in the [[United States presidential election, 1872|1872 presidential election]]
*[[Luisa Capetillo]] (1879-1922) - [[Puerto Rico|Puerto Rican]] [[trade union|labor union]] suffragette; jailed for wearing pants in public
*[[Unity Dow]] (born 1959) - [[Botswana|Botswanan]] judge and writer, plaintiff in a case that allowed children of Botswanan women and foreign nationals to be considered [[Batswana]]
*[[Carolyn Egan]] (birthdate unknown) - [[Canada|Canadian]]-American trade unionist and feminist, advocate for women’s reproductive rights, including access to birth control, abortion, and sex education
*[[Nawal el-Saadawi]] (born 1931) - Egyptian writer and doctor, advocate for women’s health and equality
*[[Marianne Hainisch]] (1839-1936) - [[Austria|Austrian]] activist, proponent of women’s right to work and to receive education
*[[Sor Juana]] (c. 1651-1695) - [[Mexico|Mexican]] [[nun]], scholar, and proponent of women’s education
*[[Kartini|Raden Adjeng Kartini]] (1879-1904) - [[Javanese]] advocate for native [[Indonesia|Indonesian]] women, critic of polygamous marriages and lack of education opportunities for women
*[[Begum Ra'ana Liaquat Ali Khan]] (1905-1990) - [[India|Indian]]-[[Pakistan|Pakistani]] activist, founder of the All Pakistan Women’s Association, organizer of women’s nursing and first aid corps to help refugees in Delhi despite public resistance to women working outside the home
*[[Jyotiba Phule]] (1827-1890) - [[India|Indian]] social reformer, critic of the [[Indian caste system|caste system]], founded a school for girls, a widow-remarriage initiative, a home for upper caste widows, and a home for infant girls to discourage female infanticide
*[[Dora Russell]] (1894-1986) - British progressive campaigner, advocate of marriage reform, birth control and female emancipation
*[[Hoda Shaarawi]] (1879-1947) - Egyptian feminist, organizer for the Mubarrat Muhammad Ali (women’s social service organization), the Union of Educated Egyption Women and the Wafdist Women’s Central Committee, founder and first president of the [[Egyptian Feminist Union]]
*[[Shamima Shaikh]] (1960-1998) - [[South Africa|South African]] activist, member of the Muslim Youth Movement of South Africa, proponent of Islamic gender equality
*[[Kate Sheppard]] (1847-1934) - [[New Zealand]] suffragette, influential in winning voting rights for women in 1893 (the first national election in which women were allowed to vote) 
*[[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] (1815-1902) - [[United States|American]] social activist, abolitionist, and suffragette, organizer of the [[1848 Women's Rights Convention]], co-founder of the [[National Woman's Suffrage Association]] and the [[International Council of Women]]
*[[Ida B. Wells]] (1862-1931) - [[United States|American]] civil rights and anti-[[lynching]] activist, suffragette noted for her refusal to avoid media attention because she was [[African American]]
*[[Mary Wollstonecraft]] (1759-1797) - author of ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Women]],'' advocate of women’s equality and rationality
*[[Emmeline Pankhurst]] (1858 – 1928) was one of the founders of the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[suffragette]] movement

==Freedoms granted by religions==
{|style="width:90%; background:#efefef; "  border="1" cellpadding="7" cellspacing="0"
|- style="background:#ffdead;"
| [[Religion]]
| [[Roman Catholicism]]
| [[Protestantism]]
| [[Islam]]
| [[Hinduism]]
| [[Buddhism]]
| [[Sikhism]]
| [[Judaism]]
| [[Neopaganism]]
|-
| [[Right to vote]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Public office|Hold Public Office]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Part
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Work|to Work]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Equal pay]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Property|Own Property]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Education]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Marriage]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Parenting]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Religious|Religious Office]]
| Part
| Part
| No
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Lead a religious assembly]]
| No
| Part
| No
| No
| No
| Yes
| Part
| Yes
|-
| [[Military|Military Service]]
| Part
| Part
| Part
| Part
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|-
| [[Contract|Legal Contract]]
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
| Yes
|}

===Sikhism===
{{Main|Women in Sikhism}}

The [[Sikh]] religion grants women equal status in most aspects of life. Women are allowed to lead religious assemblies; to perform [[Kirtan]] (Congregational hymn singing); become members of religious management committees; to lead armies on the battlefield; equality in marriage; equality in [[Amrit]]; etc

[[Guru Nanak]] (1469-1539) the founder [[Sikh Guru]] is probably the first recorded religious prophet to grant women equal rights as men. The primary teachings of [[Sikhism]] are recorded in the [[Sikh]] holy book called the [[Sri Guru Granth Sahib]]. He is quoted in this [[Granth]] to have said:
{{Quotation|From woman, man is born; within woman, man is conceived; &lt;br&gt;
to woman he is engaged and married. &lt;br&gt;
Woman becomes his friend; through woman, the future generations come. &lt;br&gt;
When his woman dies, he seeks another woman; to woman he is bound. &lt;br&gt;
So why call her bad? From her, kings are born. &lt;br&gt;
From woman, woman is born; without woman, there would be no one at all.'' &lt;br&gt;
&amp;mdash; Guru Nanak, Raag Aasaa Mehal 1, [[SGGS]], Page 473}}

In the East, up until 1500's, women had generally being treated almost as [[untouchable]] and had very few rights. [http://www.geocities.com/~abdulwahid/hinduism/hindu_women.html &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;] They were subjected to highly degrading practises like [[Purdah]] (wearing of a veil to cover their face as a sign of inferiority and submission); [[Sati]], the killing of the wife on the dead husband's funeral pyre; [[child marriage]], when girls of between 5 and 10 years old were married off, without their consent or knowledge; [[Dowry]], the giving of expensive gifts by the bride's family to the groom's family in agreement to the wedding; etc.  To root out these century old habits, the Guru spoke clearly and in simple terms to influence the masses

To reinforce the message of equality among the genders, the Sikh founder Guru further says in the Sikh holy book [[Sri Guru Granth Sahib]] that God's light shine in both men and women thus: ''"In the earth and in the sky, I do not see any second.  Among all the '''women and the men''', His Light is shining. (3)"'' ([[SGGS]] page 223). To further remove the long ingrained prejudices of the masses, Guru Nanak also says that both men and women are created by the Lord thus: ''"He Himself '''created all women and men'''; the Lord Himself plays every play."'' (SGGS page 304) and again ''"Women and men, all the men and women, all came from the One Primal Lord God."'' (SGGS page 983). Further to make sure that people of both the [[Muslim]] and [[Hindu]] religions were listening, [[Bhagat Kabir]] say this: ''"You fashioned all these men and women, Lord. All these are Your Forms. Kabeer is the child of God, Allah, Raam. All the Gurus and prophets are mine. ||5||"''  (SGGS page 1349), mentioning that "God", [[Allah]] (the Muslim name for God) and [[Raam]] (the Hindu name for God) are all honoured.

From the 1500's, the women in [[India]] had support from the [[Sikh Gurus]] and the wrongful practise of discrimination against women very slowly began to disappear from this region. However, due to entrenched position of various sub-cultures within the sub-continent, cases of gender discrimination are still present in small numbers in various parts of this region, especially in rural communities.

==See also==
* [[Equal Rights Amendment]] (ERA)
* [[Feminism]] - the core ideology behind women's rights 
* [[International Women's Rights Action Watch]] ([[IWRAW]])
* [[Legal rights of women in history]]
* [[Reproductive rights]] - within "women's rights," issues regarding "reproductive freedom"
* The [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]] (CEDAW)
* [[List of suffragists and suffragettes]]
* [[List of democracy and elections-related topics]] 
* [[suffragette]]
* [[League of Women Voters]]
* [[National Woman's Suffrage Association]]
* [[Seneca Falls Convention]], [[Seneca Falls Declaration of Sentiments]]
* ''[[The New Northwest]]''
* [[Women in the Victorian Era]]
* [[Women in Sikhism]]
* [[Women's political rights in Bahrain]]
* [[Section Twenty-eight of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]]
* [[Women's suffrage in South Carolina]]
* [[Women's suffrage]]

==External links==
* [http://roedepot.com Roe Depot ~ a forum on reproductive rights &amp; alternative birth control]
* [http://www.ansarburney.org/ Ansar Burney Trust] working for women's rights in the Middle East
* [http://www.hrw.org/women/ Human Rights Watch: Women's Rights]
* [http://othello.alma.edu/~07tmhopk/womeninthechurch.html Women in the (Christian) Church] essay arguing against ordination of women in the Christian church
* [http://www.loadedissues.com Women's Rights]


[[Category:Women's rights| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>