<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071105221912|169469581" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="145439" pageid="145439" ns="0" title="Women&#039;s rights"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-12T01:06:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{sprotect|small=yes}}
{{Refimprove|date=August 2007}}
{{rights}}
The term '''women’s rights''' refers to the [[Freedom (political)|freedoms]] inherently possessed by women and girls of all ages, which may be institutionalized, ignored or suppressed by law, custom, and behavior in a particular society. These liberties are grouped together and differentiated from broader notions of [[human rights]] because they often differ from the freedoms inherently possessed by or recognized for men and boys, and because activism surrounding this issue claims an inherent historical and traditional bias against the exercise of rights by women.

Issues commonly associated with notions of women's rights include, though are not limited to, the right: to bodily integrity and autonomy; to vote (universal suffrage); to hold public office; to work; to fair wages or equal pay; to own property; to education; to serve in the military; to enter into legal contracts; and to have marital, parental and religious rights.&lt;ref name=quarterly&gt; Lockwood, Bert B. (ed.), ''Women's Rights: A "Human Rights Quarterly" Reader'' (John Hopkins University Press, 2006), ISBN 9780801883743&lt;/ref&gt;  Women and their supporters have campaigned and in some places continue to campaigned for the same rights as modern men.&lt;ref name=quarterly/&gt;

==A history of Women's rights==
===Historical background===
Till the mid nineteenth century, writers assumed that a [[Patriarchy|patriarchal order]] was a natural order that had existed&lt;ref name="Maine"&gt;Maine, Henry Sumner. Ancient Law 1861&lt;/ref&gt;
as JS Mill wrote, since "the very earliest twilight of human society".&lt;ref name=mill"&gt;
JS Mill The subjection of women 1859&lt;/ref&gt; This was not seriously challenged till the eighteenth century when Jesuit missionaries found matrilineality in native North American peoples.&lt;ref&gt;[[Joseph-François Lafitau|Lafitau, Joseph François]]. cited by Campbell, Joseph in, Myth, religion, and mother-right:  selected writings of JJ Bachofen. Manheim, R (trans.) Princeton, N.J. 1967 introduction xxxiii&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 16th century the [[Reformation]] allowed more women to add their voices. These include [[Jane Anger]], [[Emilia Lanier|Aemilia Lanyer]], and [[Anna Trapnell]].  However, it is argued that the [[Dissolution of the Monasteries|closure of convents]] deprived women of one path to education &lt;ref&gt;Wright, Stephanie Hodgson. Women's writings of the early modern period 1588-1688. Edinburgh University 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hobby, Elaine. Virtue of necessity: English women's writing 1649-88. University of Michigan 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="lerner"&gt; Lerner, Gerda. The Creation of Feminist Consciousness From the Middle Ages to Eighteen-seventy. Oxford University Press, 1993&lt;/ref&gt;  Giving voice in the secular context was more difficult, deprived of the rationale and protection of divine inspiration. [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]] demonstrated leadership amongst women, even if unsupportive of their causes, and was a role model for the [[education of women]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.womenwriters.net/editorials/elliott.htm] Elliott, Kimberly. "Eliza's works, wars, praise": Representations of Elizabeth I in Diana Primrose and Anne Bradstreet. Womenwriters.net December 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Enlightenment &amp; ''A Vindication of the Rights of Woman'' ===
[[Image:Wollstonecraft-right-of-woman.jpg|thumb|right|300px|First edition print of ''Vindication of the Rights of Woman: with Strictures on Political and Moral Subjects'']]
{{main|A Vindication of the Rights of Woman}}
{{main|History_of_feminism#Eighteenth_Century:_The_Age_of_Enlightenment}}
[[The Age of Enlightenment]] was characterized by secular intellectual reasoning, and a flowering of philosophical writing. The most important feminist writer of the time was [[Mary Wollstonecraft]], often described as the first feminist philosopher. ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Woman]]'' ([[1792]]).  Wollstonecraft argued that it was the education and upbringing of women that created  limited expectations.  Despite some inconsistencies (Brody refers to the "Two Wollestoncrafts"&lt;ref&gt;Brody, Miriam. Mary Wollstonecraft: Sexuality and women's rights (1759-1797), in Spender, Dale (ed.) Feminist theorists: Three centuries of key women thinkers, Pantheon 1983, pp. 40-59 ISBN 0-394-53438-7&lt;/ref&gt;
) reflective of problems that had no easy answers, this book remains a foundation stone of feminist thought.&lt;ref name=Walters&gt; Walters, Margaret, ''Feminism: A very short introduction'' (Oxford, 2005), ISBN 978019280510X&lt;/ref&gt;

In other parts of Europe, [[Hedvig Charlotta Nordenflycht]] was writing in Sweden, and what is thought to be the first scientific society for women was founded in [[Middelburg]], in the south of Holland in 1785. This was the Natuurkundig Genootschap der Dames (Women's Society for Natural Knowledge).&lt;ref&gt;Jacob, Margaret C., Sturkenboom, Dorothée. A women's scientific Society in the west: The late eighteenth-century assimilation of science. Isis 2003 9492): 217-52&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stilus.nl/sturkenboom/o-0505.htm The electric kiss: Ladies, physics and friendship in the 18th and 19th centuries]&lt;/ref&gt;
which met regularly to 1881, finally dissolving in 1887. However Deborah Crocker and Sethanne Howard point out that women have been scientists for 4,000 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.astr.ua.edu/4000WS/4000WS.html Crocker, Deborah and Sethanne Howard. 4000 years of women in science]&lt;/ref&gt;
Journals for women which focused on science became popular during this period as well.&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, Patricia. The scientific lady: A social history of women's scientific interests 1520-1918. St Martin's, N.Y. 1990&lt;/ref&gt;

===Suffrage, the right to vote===
{{main|Women's suffrage}}

The ideas that were planted in the late 1700s took root during the 1800s. Women began to agitate for the [[right to vote]] and participate in government and law making.&lt;ref name=Krolokke&gt; Krolokke, Charlotte and Anne Scott Sorensen, 'From Suffragettes to Grrls' in Gender Communication Theories and Analyses:From Silence to Performance (Sage, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States====
{{Main|History of women's suffrage in the United States}}
American women advocated women's right to vote from the 1820s onward. These was achieved in the territories of [[Wyoming Territory|Wyoming]] (1869) and [[Utah Territory|Utah]] (1870), although Utah women were disenfranchised by the [[United States Congress|U.S. Congress]] in 1887.&lt;ref name=Flexner&gt;Flexner, Eleanor, Century of Struggle: The Woman's Rights Movement in the United States (The Belknap Press, 1996), ISBN 9780674106539&lt;/ref&gt;  The push to grant Utah women's suffrage was at least partially fueled by outsiders' belief that, given the right to vote, Utah women would dispose of [[polygamy]].  It was only after Utah women exercised their suffrage rights in favor of polygamy that the U.S. Congress disenfranchised Utah women.&lt;ref name=Van_Wagenen&gt;Van Wagenen, Lola: "Sister-Wives and Suffragists: Polygamy and the Politics of Woman Suffrage 1870–1896," BYU Studies, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Other territories and states granted women the right to vote in the late 19th and early 20th century, but national women's suffrage did not come until the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] was ratified in 1920.&lt;ref&gt;Stevens, Doris, Jailed for Freedom: American Women Win the Vote (NewSage Press, 1995), ISBN 9780939165252&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wheeler, Marjorie Spruill, ed., One Woman, One Vote: Rediscovering the Woman Suffrage Movement (NewSage Press, 1995) ISBN 9780939165260&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Flexner/&gt;

====Great Britain====

In [[Great Britain]], women reformers were divided into two groups — the [[National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies]] and the [[Women's Social and Political Union]]. Leaders in the struggle were the radical [[Emmeline Pankhurst]] and her daughter [[Christabel Pankhurst|Christabel]]. Their fight also proved slow and frustrating. In 1918 the [[British Parliament]] finally passed a bill allowing women over the age of 30 to vote. In 1928 the age limit was lowered to 21.&lt;ref name=X&gt; Phillips, Melanie, The Ascent of Woman: A History of the Suffragette Movement (Abacus, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt;
{{seealso|Women in the Victorian Era}}

====Other countries====

In some nations women were granted full voting rights earlier than in the United States and Britain. Women won the right to vote in [[New Zealand]] in 1893, [[Australia]] in 1902, and [[Finland]] in 1906. But many other nations proved much slower to change. For example, women in [[France]] were not given voting rights until 1944. However, in some of these countries only women in the ruling population were able to vote at first. For example, [[Indigenous Australians|Aboriginal]] women in Australia were not allowed to vote until they became citizens in 1967.&lt;ref&gt;http://womenshistory.about.com/od/suffrage/a/intl_timeline_3.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.parliament.vic.gov.au/women.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://faculty.marianopolis.edu/c.belanger/quebechistory/encyclopedia/Canada-WomensVote-WomenSuffrage.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  Today women in some conservative [[Arab countries]] still do not have the right to vote.{{Facts|date=November 2007}}

{{seealso|Third-world_feminism}}

==The modern movement==
{{related|[[Reproductive rights]]}}

In the 1960s women's rights again became an important issue in the [[United States]]. Now the movement was called “[[feminism]]” or “women's liberation.” Reformers wanted the same pay as men, an equal rights amendment to the U.S. Constitution, and the freedom to plan their families or not have children at all. Their efforts were met with mixed results.{{Facts|date=November 2007}}

In 1966 the [[National Organization of Women]] (NOW) was created with the purpose of bringing about equality for all women. NOW was one important group that fought for the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] (ERA). This amendment stated that “equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or any state on account of [[gender|sex]].” But there was disagreement on how the proposed amendment would be understood. Supporters believed it would guarantee women equal treatment. But critics feared it might deny women the right be financially supported by their husbands. The amendment died in 1982 because not enough states had ratified it. ERAs have been included in subsequent Congressses, but have still failed to be ratified. {{Facts|date=November 2007}}

In the last three decades of the 20th century, American women knew a new freedom: medical advances helped them control if and when they would have children. Called [[birth control]], this enabled women to plan their adult lives, often making way for both career and family. The movement had been started in the 1910s by pioneering social reformer [[Margaret Sanger]].{{Facts|date=November 2007}}

Over the course of the 20th century women took on a greater role in society. For example, many women served in the [[U.S. government]] — some as [[senators]] and others as members of the [[President's Cabinet]]. Many women took advantage of opportunities to become educated. In the United States at the beginning of the 20th century less than 20 percent of all college degrees were earned by women. By the end of the century this figure had risen to about 50 percent.{{Facts|date=November 2007}}

Opportunities also expanded in the [[workplace]]. Fields such as medicine, law, and science opened to include more women. At the beginning of the 20th century about 5 percent of the doctors in the United States were women. As of 1998, 23 percent of all doctors were women, and today, women make up more than 50 percent of the medical student population. While the numbers of women in these fields increased, many women still continued to hold clerical, factory, retail, or service jobs. For example, they worked as office assistants, on assembly lines, or as cooks.{{Facts|date=November 2007}}

== The United Nations and women's rights ==
In 1946 the [[United Nations]] established a [[United Nations Commission on the Status of Women|Commission on the Status of Women]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/Review/ UN Department of Economic and Social Affairs. Division for the Advancement of Women]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/CSW60YRS/CSWbriefhistory.pdf Short History of the Commission on the Status of Women]&lt;/ref&gt;
Originally as the Section on the Status of Women, Human Rights Division, Department of Social Affairs, and now part of the [[United Nations Economic and Social Council|Economic and Social Council]] (ECOSOC). In 1948 the UN issued its [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/udhr/ Universal Declaration of Human Rights]&lt;/ref&gt;
which protects "the equal rights of men and women", and addressed both the equality and equity issues. Since 1975 the UN has held a series of world conferences on women's issues, starting with the World Conference of the International Women's Year in Mexico City.  These conferences created an international forum for women's rights, but also illustrated divisions between women of different cultures and the difficulties of attempting to apply principles universally&lt;ref name=Catagay&gt;Catagay, N., Grown, C. and Santiago, A. 1986. "The Nairobi Women's Conference: Toward a Global Feminism?" Feminist Studies, 12, 2:401–412&lt;/ref&gt;  Emerging from the 1985 Nairobi conference was a realization that feminism is not monolithic but "''constitutes the political expression of the concerns and interests of women from different regions, classes, nationalities, and ethnic backgrounds. There is and must be a diversity of feminisms, responsive to the different needs and concerns of women, and defined by them for themselves. This diversity builds on a common opposition to gender oppression and hierarchy which, however, is only the first step in articulating and acting upon a political agenda.''"&lt;ref name=Sen_&amp;_Grown&gt;Sen, G., Grown, C.  Development, crisis and alternative visions: Third World women’s perspectives. Monthly Review Press,
N.Y. 1987&lt;/ref&gt;  At the [[Fourth World Conference on Women]] in Beijing, ''The Platform for Action'' was signed. This included a commitment to achieve "[[gender equality]] and the empowerment of women".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/index.html Fourth World Conference on Women. Beijing, China. September 1995. Action for Equality, Development and Peace]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;United Nations [http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/text/econvention.htm#intro ''Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women'': Introduction]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable women’s rights activists==
:''See: [[List of women's rights activists]]; [[List of suffragists and suffragettes]]''

==See also==
*[[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]] (CEDAW)
*[[National American Woman Suffrage Association]]
*[[League of Women Voters]]
*[[Canadian Women's Suffrage Association]]
*[[National Woman's Suffrage Association]]
*[[Pregnant patients' rights]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/ UN Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]
*[http://www.hrw.org/women/ Human Rights Watch: Women's Rights]
*[http://www.omct.org/index.php?id=EQL&amp;lang=eng World Organization Against Torture: No Violence Against Women]

[[Category:Women's rights| ]]

[[es:Derechos de la mujer]]
[[fr:Droits des femmes]]
[[pt:Direitos da Mulher]]
[[sk:ženské práva]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>