<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221028203243|1118775414" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14433622" pageid="14433622" ns="0" title="Women in the workforce"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-18T16:42:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|All women who perform some kind of job}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2022}}{{Redirect|Working woman||Working Woman (disambiguation){{!}}Working Woman}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{More footnotes|date=June 2020}}
{{Incomplete|pre-Modern era|date=June 2020}}}}
[[File:Tanzania hospital information mgt system.jpg|thumb|upright=1.6|A woman employee demonstrates a hospital information management system in Tanzania.]]
[[File:Women in workforce.png|thumb|Female labor force participation rate, ages 15-64 (World Bank/ILO, 2019)]]
[[File:Proportion of women in senior and middle management positions, OWID.svg|thumb|upright=1.6|Proportion of women in senior and middle management positions (2017)]]
Since the [[industrial revolution]], participation of '''women in the workforce''' outside the home has increased in industrialized nations, with particularly large growth seen in the 20th century. Largely seen as a boon for industrial society, women in the workforce contribute to a higher national economic output as measure in GDP as well as decreasing labor costs by increasing the labor supply in a society.

Women's lack of access to [[higher education]] had effectively excluded them from the practice of well-paid and high status occupations. Entry of women into the higher professions, like [[law]] and [[medicine]], was delayed in most countries due to women being denied entry to universities and qualification for degrees. For example, [[Cambridge University]] only fully validated degrees for women late in 1947, and even then only after much opposition and acrimonious debate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.admin.cam.ac.uk/news/press/factsheets/women2.html]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071107063131/http://www.admin.cam.ac.uk/news/press/factsheets/women2.html|date=November 7, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women were largely limited to low-paid and poor status occupations for most of the 19th and 20th centuries, or earned less pay than men for doing the same work.{{strip categories|{{citation needed|date=March 2021}}}} However, through the 20th century, the [[labor market]] shifted.  [[Office work]] that does not require heavy labor expanded and women increasingly acquired the higher education that led to better-compensated, longer-term [[career]]s rather than lower-skilled, shorter-term jobs. Mothers are less likely to be employed unlike men and women without children.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Statistical Overview of Women in Global Workplaces: Catalyst Quick Take|url=https://www.catalyst.org/research/women-in-the-workforce-global/|access-date=2021-05-20|website=Catalyst|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The increasing rates of women contributing in the work force has led to a more equal disbursement of [[working hours|hours worked]] across the regions of the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gapminder.org/world/#$majorMode=chart$is;shi=t;ly=2003;lb=f;il=t;fs=11;al=30;stl=t;st=t;nsl=t;se=t$wst;tts=C$ts;sp=5.59290322580644;ti=2007$zpv;v=0$inc_x;mmid=XCOORDS;iid=rOXvRa2ZC2oXqBn7gz62IMg;by=ind$inc_y;mmid=YCOORDS;iid=rdCufG2vozTpKw7TBGbyoWw;by=ind$inc_s;uniValue=8.21;iid=phAwcNAVuyj0XOoBL_n5tAQ;by=ind$inc_c;uniValue=255;gid=CATID0;by=grp$map_x;scale=lin;dataMin=7.8;dataMax=86$map_y;scale=lin;dataMin=26;dataMax=56$map_s;sma=49;smi=2.65$cd;bd=0$inds=|title=Graph|publisher=[[Gapminder World]] |access-date=17 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=March 2019}} However, in western European countries the nature of women's employment participation remains markedly different from that of men.

In 2017 there are around 74.6&amp;nbsp;million women in the U.S. civilian labor force.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=12 Stats About Working Women {{!}} U.S. Department of Labor Blog|url=https://blog.dol.gov/2017/03/01/12-stats-about-working-women|access-date=2020-11-10|website=blog.dol.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Areas of study ==
{{Globalize|section|West|date=June 2020}}
{{Women in society sidebar}}
As the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] raged in the U.S., [[Virginia Penny]] of [[Louisville, Kentucky]], finished her research project and published the ground-breaking 1862 book, ''How women can make money married or single, in all branches of the arts and sciences, professions, trades, agricultural and mechanical pursuits''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldcat.org/title/how-women-can-make-money-married-or-single-in-all-branches-of-the-arts-and-sciences-professions-trades-agricultural-and-mechanical-pursuits/oclc/15690614 ''How women can make money married or single, in all branches of the arts and sciences, professions, trades, agricultural and mechanical pursuits'' (Philadelphia, 1862)]&lt;/ref&gt;  Hoping to offer hard facts about what women in the workforce would encounter, Penny had interviewed thousands of employers, using both a survey via the postal mail and in person – when she would also interview workers.  Many of her site visits were in Philadelphia, New York and Boston.  She distilled her research to list over 500 jobs that were open to women as well as the information about the jobs and potential availability for women.  She also indicated when employers offered their reasons for wage differentials based on gender.

She dedicated her book "to worthy and industrious women in the United States, striving to earn a livelihood", and the book gained much attention from reviewers and scholars across the country.  She sold her rights to the book to another publisher who put it out as an encyclopaedia, ''The Employments of Women: A Cyclopaedia of Woman's Work'',&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=xR0EAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''The Employments of Women: A Cyclopaedia of Woman's Work'']&lt;/ref&gt; in 1863. It sold better once it was re-titled again in 1870 as ''How Women Can Make Money, Married or Single''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Gensemer|first1=Susan H.
 |title=Penny, Virginia
 |url=http://www.anb.org/articles/14/14-01170.html
 |website=American National Biography Online
 |publisher=American Council of Learned Societies|access-date=21 December 2016|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In its several different versions, 36 editions were published between 1862 and 2006, and six editions of the adaptation in German (first published in 1867).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Penny, Virginia 1826-
 |url=http://worldcat.org/identities/lccn-n90694085/
 |website=OCLC WorldCat Identities
 |publisher=OCLC Online Computer Library Center, Inc.|access-date=21 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the twentieth century, [[division of labor]] by [[gender]] has been studied most systematically in [[women's studies]] (especially [[women's history]], which has frequently examined the history and biography of women's participation in particular fields) and [[gender studies]] more broadly. Occupational studies, such as the [[history of medicine]] or studies of [[professionalization]], also examine questions of gender, and the roles of women in the history of particular fields. Women dominate as accountants, auditors, and psychologists.&lt;ref name="Witz-1990"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Anne Witz | title = Patriarchy and Professions: The Gendered Politics of Occupational Closure | journal = Sociology | volume = 24 | issue = 4 | date = 1990 | pages = 675–690 | doi = 10.1177/0038038590024004007 | s2cid = 143826607 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Cavanagh-2003"&gt;{{cite journal|author=S. A. L. Cavanagh|title=The Gender of Professionalism and Occupational Closure: the management of tenure-related disputes by the 'Federation of Women Teachers' Associations of Ontario' 1918–1949|journal=Gender and Education|volume=15|publisher=Gender and Education, 15.1|date=March 2003|pages=39–57|doi=10.1080/0954025032000042130|s2cid=144632048}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Mahony-1990"&gt;{{Cite journal |author1=Karen Mahony  |author2=Brett Van Toen  |name-list-style=amp | title = Mathematical Formalism as a Means of Occupational Closure in Computing—Why "Hard" Computing Tends to Exclude Women | journal = Gender and Education | volume = 2 | issue = 3 | date = 1990 | pages = 319–331 | url = http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ422280&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=eric_accno&amp;accno=EJ422280 | doi=10.1080/0954025900020306}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, modern [[civil right]]s law has frequently examined gender restrictions of access to a field of occupation; [[gender discrimination]] within a field; and gender harassment in particular workplaces. This body of law is called [[employment discrimination|employment discrimination law]], and gender and race discrimination are the largest sub-sections within the area. Laws specifically aimed at preventing discrimination against women have been passed in many countries; see, e.g., the [[Pregnancy Discrimination Act]] in the United States.

== Women and economic development ==
{{Cleanup|reason=references formatted improperly|date=November 2020}}
[[File:Women in informal employment as share of female employment, OWID.svg|thumb|upright=2|Women in informal employment as share of female employment in 2017&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Women in informal employment as share of female employment |url=https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/women-in-informal-employment-as-share-of-female-employment |website=Our World in Data |access-date=5 March 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Global research clearly delineates the correlation between women's role in the economy and an increase in the standard of living. In the 2001 [[World Bank]] report entitled "Engendering Development", the connection between women's involvement in the economy and growth is more clearly stated:&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite book|last1=King|first1=Elizabeth|last2=Mason|first2=Andrew|date=2001-01-31|title=Engendering Development|url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1596/0-1952-1596-6|doi=10.1596/0-1952-1596-6|isbn=978-0-19-521596-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;While disparities in basic rights; in schooling, credit, and jobs; or in the ability to participate in public life take their most direct toll on women and girls, the full costs of gender inequality ultimately harm everyone…ignoring gender disparities comes at a great cost—to people's well-being and to countries' abilities to grow sustainably, to govern effectively, and thus reduce poverty.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Society's intrinsic value is often associated with contribution and production as a whole, thus women's inability to participate in economy further solidifies a subordinate role in society. "The fact that women have fewer opportunities in labor market may contribute to their unequal treatment in the household…Increased opportunities for women in the labor market do indeed translate into better outcomes for women…For the same increase in total household income, an increase in female income of 7 U.S. dollars per month translates into a 1 percentage point increase in the survival rate for girls."&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Duflo|first=Esther|date=2012|title=Women Empowerment and Economic Development|journal=Journal of Economic Literature|volume=50|issue=4|pages=1051–1079|doi=10.1257/jel.50.4.1051|hdl=1721.1/82663|s2cid=17267963|hdl-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women are treated as less than men because their role in the home does not perpetuate survival of the family directly in terms of income. A stark realization of women's economic value in the eyes of under-developed countries is sex selective abortion rights and the alarming phenomenon of "missing women."&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; What many societies fail to realize is that the trade-off to helping a woman instead of a man does not exist. When a woman is empowered with education and involvement in the economy everyone is better off. Women's economic involvement will drive up Gross Domestic Product (GDP) which is a foundational standard for higher living. James Wolfensohn of the World Bank states, "Education for girls has a catalytic effect on every dimension of development: lower child and maternal mortality rates; increased educational attainment by daughters and sons; higher productivity; and improved environmental management. Together, these can mean faster economic growth and, equally important, wider distribution of the fruits of growth… More education for girls will also enable more and more women to attain leadership positions at all levels of society: from health clinics in the villages to parliaments in the capitals. This, in turn, will change the way societies will deal with problems and raise the quality of global decision-making."&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

== Paid employment globally ==
[[File:Changes in percentages of professionals by gender.png|thumbnail|This chart depicts the change in the percentage of women in three professional occupations (dentist, physician, lawyer), from 1970 to 2007.]]
Women still contribute to their communities in many regions mainly through agricultural work. In Southern Asia, Western Asia, and Africa, only 20% of women work at paid non-agricultural jobs. Worldwide, women's rate of paid employment outside of agriculture grew to 41% by 2008.{{sfn|Kinnear|2011|page=222}}

One of the main forms of paid employment for women worldwide is actually a traditional one, that of the market "hawker". Women have worked outside the home as vendors at markets since ancient times in many parts of the world, such as Central America, South Asia, and Africa.

During the 20th century, the most significant global shift in women's paid employment came from the spread of global travel and the development of a large migrant workforce of women [[domestic workers]] seeking jobs outside of their native country. The [[Philippines]] is a major source of female domestic workers. Before the 1990s, the majority of Filipinos working outside the Philippines were male, but by 2012, an estimated 63% of Filipinos working overseas were female.&lt;ref name="Tubeza"&gt;{{cite news|last=Tubeza|first=Philip C.|title=Overseas deployment of Filipino domestic workers continues to rise|newspaper=Philippine Daily Inquirer|publisher=Inquirer Global Nation|url=http://globalnation.inquirer.net/32067/overseas-deployment-of-filipino-domestic-workers-continues-to-rise|date=April 7, 2012|access-date=May 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Estimates of Filipino women working overseas are in the millions. Over 138,000 new domestic workers gained permission to work overseas in 2012, a number that grew 12% from the previous year.&lt;ref name="Tubeza"/&gt; Overseas employment often results in the women leaving their own children behind in the Philippines to be cared for by relatives. Domestic employees from the Philippines and other countries have also been subject to exploitation and sex and money extreme abuse, for example in several countries in the Middle East, where they are often employed. It is estimated that [[remittances]] from overseas workers (both male and female) bring $1&amp;nbsp;billion (USD) per month to the Philippines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=King|first=Russell|title=People on the Move: An atlas of migration|publisher=University of California Press|year=2010|isbn=978-0-520-26151-8|pages=[https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/78 78–9]|url=https://archive.org/details/peopleonmoveatla0000unse/page/78}}&lt;/ref&gt;

33% of the drivers and station controllers in the [[Bangalore]] metro are female in an effort to create a more welcoming and diverse workplace. Children of employees have access to childcare facilities, while women drivers can work at stations near to their homes and have access to a separate recreation area. If women are unable to perform night shifts, they work in the mornings or evenings. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Reporter |first=Staff |date=2016-05-07 |title=These women take the driver’s seat, both at home and at work |language=en-IN |work=The Hindu |url=https://www.thehindu.com/news/cities/bangalore/these-women-take-the-drivers-seat-both-at-home-and-at-work/article8571564.ece |access-date=2022-10-24 |issn=0971-751X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Workforce participation by sector===
[[File:Computer industry entrepreneur workshop.jpg|thumb|Attendees at a computer business networking event for potential entrepreneurs, United States]]
[[File:Woodstock press photographer.jpg|thumb|A woman press photographer covers a music fest, Poland, 2008]]

Women and men often participate in economic sectors in sharply different proportions, a result of gender clustering in occupations. Reasons for this may include a traditional association of certain types of work with a particular gender. There is a wide range of other possible economic, social and cultural variables that impact the gender distribution in different occupations, including within a region or country. An averaging of statistics gathered by the United Nations for 2004 through 2007 reflects these differences (totals may not add up to 100% due to rounding):

'''Sectoral distribution of employed persons, by sector and sex (2004 through 2007)'''&lt;ref name="The World's Women 2010"&gt;{{cite web|title=The World's Women 2010|url=http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/products/Worldswomen/WW_full%20report_color.pdf|publisher=United Nations|access-date=May 15, 2012|pages=84}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More detailed statistics show large differences even within these regions. For example, 11% of employed women in East Asia are employed in agriculture, a number that rises to 55% in South Asia; 70% of women in Southern Africa are employed in the service sector, while in Eastern, Middle, and Western Africa this number is 26%.&lt;ref name="The World's Women 2010"/&gt;

According to the International Labour Organization, women's involvement in the labor force declines by 16.5% in developing nations as a result of unsafe public transportation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Addressing women’s safety concerns in public transport in Jordan to boost their economic activity |url=https://blogs.worldbank.org/arabvoices/addressing-womens-safety-concerns-public-transport-jordan-boost-their-economic-activity |access-date=2022-10-24 |website=blogs.worldbank.org |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=World Bank and UN Women Launch Course on Managing Gender Equality in Transportation |url=https://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2021/03/05/world-bank-and-un-women-launch-course-on-managing-gender-equality-in-transportation |access-date=2022-10-24 |website=World Bank |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Occupational dissimilarity index===
Choice of occupation is considered to be one of the key factors contributing to the male-female wage differential. In other words, careers with a majority of female employees tend to pay less than careers that employ a majority of males. This is different from direct wage discrimination within occupations, as males in the female-dominated professions will also make lower than average wages and the women in the ]r for the wage differential to disappear. In 1960, the similarity index for the United State Women's Trade Union League (WTUL) is established to advocate for improved wages and working conditions for women. In 1920 The Women's Bureau of the Department of Labor was formed to create equal rights and a safe workplace for women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoplease.com/spot/womenstimeline2.html#ixzz3Vlm8PLZb Women's Rights Movement in the U.S.: Timeline of Events (1921–1979).]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1956 a group called Financial Women's Association (FWA), was formed. It is an organisation with special emphasis on the role and development of women, to attain greater recognition for women's achievements in business, and to encourage women to seek career opportunities in finance and business.&lt;ref name="DiversityBestPractices"&gt;[http://www.diversitybestpractices.com/news-articles/20-womens-organizations-you-need-know "20 Women's Organizations You Need to Know"], Diversity Best Practices, February 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1966 the National Organization for Women (NOW) was founded by a group of feminists including Betty Friedan. The largest women's rights group in the U.S., NOW seeks to end sexual discrimination, especially in the workplace, by means of legislative lobbying, litigation, and public demonstrations. NOW has 500,000 contributing members and 550 chapters in all 50 states and the District of Columbia.&lt;ref&gt;MacLean, Nancy. "The American Women's Movement, 1945–2000: A Brief History with Documents." Boston: Bedford/St. Martin's, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Founded in 1972, the National Association of Female Executives (NAFE) provides education, networking and public advocacy to empower its members to achieve career success and financial security. Members are women executives, business owners, entrepreneurs and others who are committed to NAFE's mission: the advancement of women in the workplace.&lt;ref name="DiversityBestPractices" /&gt; Many of these organizations led to legal action and protecting women's rights as workers and empowered women in the workplace.

==Laws protecting women's rights as workers==
[[File:Shinzō Abe and Ivanka Trump (4).jpg|thumb|Japanese Prime Minister [[Shinzō Abe]] and First Daughter and Advisor to the former U.S. President [[Ivanka Trump]] attending the World Assembly for Women to discuss women's rights, Tokyo, 2017]]

International laws protecting women's rights as workers exist through the efforts of various international bodies.  On June 16, 2011, the [[International Labour Organization]] (ILO) passed C189 [[Convention on Domestic Workers|Domestic Workers Convention, 2011]], binding signatories to regulations intended to end abuses of migrant domestic workers. It was anticipated that the convention would put pressure on non-ratifying countries to support changes to their own laws to meet the change in international standards protecting domestic workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Switzerland – A step forward for domestic workers|newspaper=New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/17/world/europe/17briefs-Switzerland.html?gwh=9875484B408842FDAE59E701E668F0EF|date=June 16, 2011|access-date=May 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 2011, Hong Kong's High Court struck down a law preventing domestic workers from having residency rights granted to other foreign workers, a move that affected an estimated 100,000 domestic workers in Hong Kong.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=DeParle|first=Jason|title=Domestic workers convention may be landmark|newspaper=New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/09/world/domestic-workers-convention-may-be-landmark.html?_r=3&amp;pagewanted=1&amp;ref=world|date=October 9, 2011|access-date=May 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ILO has previously ratified the [[Equal Remuneration Convention]] in 1951, which came into force in 1953, the [[Discrimination (Employment and Occupation) Convention]], which went into force in 1960 and the [[Maternity Protection Convention, 2000]], which went into force in 2002. In 1966, the [[United Nations General Assembly]] adopted the [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]], which went into force in 1976. [[UNESCO]] also adopted the [[Convention against Discrimination in Education]] in 1960, which came into force in 1962.{{sfn|Kinnear|2011|pages=178–180}}  The [[International Convention on the Protection of the Rights of All Migrant Workers and Members of Their Families]], adopted by the United Nations General Assembly, went into force in 2003. The [[Home Work Convention]], adopted by the ILO, went into force in 2000;the Convention protects the rights of persons doing paid work out of their home, which is frequently women workers. It offers equal protection regarding working conditions, safety, remuneration, social security protection, access to training, minimum age of employment, and maternity protection.{{sfn|Kinnear|2011|page=184}}

[[Human trafficking]] often targets young women who are abducted and sent outside their own country to work as domestic workers, often in conditions of extreme exploitation. As of 2020, 1 out of every 130 women globally are victims of this form of 'modern slavery'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/global-health/women-and-girls/handmaids-tale-reality-one-130-women-girls-around-world-held/ |title=A 'Handmaid's Tale reality': one in 130 women and girls around the world held in modern slavery. Gender 'stacks the odds' from cradle to grave with women making up nearly three quarters of victims of abuse and exploitation |first=Georgina |last=Hayes |date=8 October 2020 |newspaper=[[Daily Telegraph]] |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of international laws have been ratified to address human trafficking of women and children.

Maternity protection measures are put in place to insure that women will not be discriminated against in the workplace once they return from having a child. They should also not be exposed to any health hazards while they are pregnant and at work. They are allowed time off for maternity leave as well, which allows them to bond with their child; this aspect of development is crucial for infants to gain proper attachment skills. Employers are expected to hold to these policies. Yet many women on maternity leave receive very small amounts of time off to allow for their health along with their babies' health. The amount of time allowed for maternity leave as well as the pay for maternity leave varies by country, with Sweden having the longest amount off with 68 weeks and the United States being one of the worst, with the typical period being 12 weeks without pay.&lt;ref&gt;Burn, S. M. (2005). Women across cultures: A global perspective. New York: McGraw-Hill.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Women in workforce leadership==
[[File:Deli womens entre network.jpg|thumb|An information technology networking social for potential entrepreneurs, New Delhi, India]]
[[File:Sheryl Sandberg, COO of Facebook (5329025804).jpg|thumb|upright|Facebook COO [[Sheryl Sandberg]] at a townhall]]

Female decision-makers from around Europe are organized in several national and European wide networks. The networks aim to promote women in decision-making positions in politics and the economy across Europe. These networks were founded in the 1980s and are often very different from the "service clubs" founded in the early days of the century, like Soroptimist and Zontas.

"Women in Management" is about women in business in usually male-dominated areas. Their motivation, their ideas and leadership styles and their ability to enter into leadership positions is the subject of most of the different networks.

As of 2009, women represented 20.9% of parliament in Europe (both houses) and 18.4% world average.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/world.htm|publisher=Inter-Parliamentary Union|title=Women in National Parliaments|access-date=17 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2009, 90 women serve in the U.S. Congress: 18 women serve in the Senate, and 73 women serve in the House Women hold about three percent of executive positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/world.htm |publisher=Center for American Women and Politics|title=Facts on Women Officeholders, Candidates and Voters|access-date=17 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the private sector, men still represent 9 out of 10 board members in European blue-chip companies, The discrepancy is widest at the very top: only 3% of these companies have a woman presiding over the highest decision-making body.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}} In the United States, women make up just 5.5% of company CEOs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/why-so-few-ceos-are-women-you-can-have-a-seat-at-the-table-and-not-be-a-player-11581003276 |title=Where Are All the Women CEOs? |first=Vanessa |last=Fuhrmans |date=February 6, 2020 |newspaper=[[The Wall Street Journal]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

List of members of the European Network of Women in Decision-making in Politics and the Economy:

*Committee of Women Elected Representatives of Local and Regional Authorities (Council of European Municipalities and Regions)
*BPW Europe, Business and Professional Women – Europe
*Association of Organisations of Mediterranean Businesswomen
*[[Eurochambres]] Women's Network
*[[European Platform of Women Scientists]]
*Network of Parliamentary Committees for Equal Opportunities for Women and Men in the European Union
*European Network to Promote Women's Entrepreneurship
*[[European Women's Lobby]]
*European Women's Lawyers Association
*CEE Network for Gender Issues
*European Women Inventors and Innovators Network
*European Women's Management Development International Network, EWMD
*Femanet – Eurocadres
*European Professional Women's Network, EPWN
*Women's Forum for the Economy and the Society

The European Union Commission has created a platform for all these networks. It also funded the [[Women to the Top]] program in 2003–2005 to bring more women into top management.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.svd.se/naringsliv/nyheter/artikel_1043415.svd|title=Gemensamt krafttag för ett mer jämställt Europa|last=Danielsson|first=Anna|date=2005-01-25|work=[[Svenska Dagbladet]]|language=sv|access-date=2009-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some organizations have been created to promote the presence of women in top responsibilities, in politics and business. One example is EWMD European Women's Management Development (cited above), a European and international network of individual and corporate members, drawn from professional organisations. Members are from all areas of business, education, politics and culture.

Women who are born into the upper class rather than the middle or lower class have a much better chance at holding higher positions of [[Power (social and political)|power]] in the work force if they choose to enter it.{{citation needed|date=September 2018}} According to a study published 2015, of the women who held C-suite jobs in the U.S., 94% played [[competitive sports]], 52% at a university level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ey.com/gl/en/newsroom/news-releases/news-sport-is-a-critical-lever-in-advancing-women-at-all-levels-according-to-new-ey-espnw-report|title=Sport is a critical lever in advancing women at all levels, according to new EY/espnW report|date=14 October 2015|access-date=22 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Barriers to equal participation==
[[File:What percentage of the US public approves of working wives., OWID.svg|thumb|upright=1.6|What percentage of the US public approves of working wives&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=What percentage of the US public approves of working wives? |url=https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/what-percentage-of-the-us-public-approves-of-working-wives |website=Our World in Data |access-date=5 March 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

As [[gender role]]s have followed the formation of agricultural and then industrial societies, newly developed [[profession]]s and fields of occupation have been frequently inflected by gender. Some of the ways in which gender affects a field include:

*Prohibitions or restrictions on members of a particular gender entering a field or studying a field
*[[Discrimination]] within a field, including wage, management, and prestige hierarchies
*Expectation that mothers, rather than fathers, should be the primary childcare providers

Note that these gender restrictions may not be universal in time and place, and that they operate to restrict both men and women. However, in practice, norms and laws have historically restricted women's access to particular occupations;civil rights laws and cases have thus primarily focused on equal access to and participation by ''women'' in the workforce. These barriers may also be manifested in hidden bias and by means of many [[microinequities]].

Many women face issues with sexual abuse while working in agriculture fields as well. Many of the women who work in these fields are undocumented and so supervisors or other male workers may take advantage of that. These women may suffer sexual abuse in order to keep their jobs and they cannot report the incident to the police because the fact that they are undocumented will be brought up and as a result they may be deported.

===Access to education and training===
[[File:Maasai women at USAID literacy event (6595762621).jpg|thumb|[[Maasai people|Maasai]] women at [[USAID]] literacy event]]
A number of occupations became "[[professionalization|professionalized]]" through the 19th and 20th centuries, gaining regulatory bodies, and passing laws or regulations requiring particular [[higher education]]al requirements. As women's access to higher education was often limited, this effectively restricted women's participation in these professionalizing occupations. For instance, women were completely forbidden access to [[Cambridge University]] until 1868, and were encumbered with a variety of restrictions until 1987 when the university adopted an equal opportunity policy.&lt;ref&gt;University of Cambridge, [http://www.admin.cam.ac.uk/news/press/factsheets/women2.html "Fact Sheet: Women at Cambridge"].&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous other institutions in the United States and Western Europe began opening their doors to women over the same period of time, but access to higher education remains a significant barrier to women's full participation in the workforce in developing countries. Even where access to higher education is formally available, women's access to the full range of occupational choices is significantly limited where access to primary education is limited through social custom.&lt;ref name="UNICEF-2007"&gt;[[UNICEF]], ''[http://www.unicef.org/sowc07/ State of the World's Children (2007)]''&lt;/ref&gt;

In low- and middle-income countries, vocational and business training program interventions are carried out with the aim of increasing employment, self-employment and income. A [[systematic review]] on vocational and business training for women in these regions summarized the evidence from thirty-five studies regarding the impacts of such training programs. The authors found that these types of programs have small positive effects on employment and income with variability across studies. They found that the effects of training may increase with a stronger gender focus of the program.&lt;ref name="ChinenHoop2017"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Chinen|first1=Marjorie|last2=Hoop|first2=Thomas|last3=Alcázar|first3=Lorena|last4=Balarin|first4=María|last5=Sennett|first5=Josh|title=Vocational and business training to improve women's labour market outcomes in low‐ and middle‐income countries: a systematic review|journal=Campbell Systematic Reviews|volume=13|issue=1|year=2017|pages=1–195|issn=1891-1803|doi=10.4073/csr.2017.16|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Food and Agriculture Organization|FAO]], in Africa, without adequate training and education in business, entrepreneurial skills, and awareness of trade issues and regulations and fluency in languages of trading partners, women will struggle to gain access to formalized economies and larger scale businesses.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Low literacy levels is often what keeps women limited to informal economic activity.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

===Access to capital===
[[File:Women's business conference bahia brazil.jpg|thumb|Governor of Bahia, Brazil, attending the first state women's business conference]]
[[File:SHG women running a cabinet manufacturing business (5103677355).jpg|thumb|Women operating a cabinet manufacturing business, India]]
Women's access to occupations requiring capital outlays is also hindered by their unequal access (statistically) to capital; this affects occupations such as entrepreneur and small business owner, farm ownership, and investor.&lt;ref&gt;"DEVELOPMENT: Gender Equality Equals Growth", ''World News'', June 2, 2004, available at [https://web.archive.org/web/20040208105312/http://www.oneworld.org/ips2/may00/23_11_078.html archive.org].&lt;/ref&gt;  Numerous [[microloan]] programs attempt to redress this imbalance, targeting women for loans or grants to establish start-up businesses or farms, having determined that aid targeted to women can disproportionately benefit a nation's economy.&lt;ref name="Northoff-2004"&gt;United Nations [[Food and Agriculture Organization]] (FAO) statistics. See Erwin Northoff, "FOOD: Women Farmers are Invisible Actors in Hunger Drama", ''World News'', 2004 February 14.&lt;/ref&gt;  While research has shown that women cultivate more than half the world's food—in sub-Saharan Africa and the Caribbean, women are responsible for up to 80% of food production—most such work is family subsistence labor, and often the family property is legally owned by the men in the family.&lt;ref name="Northoff-2004" /&gt;

In Africa, women have limited access to financial services and formalized assets such as titles and deeds; this results in low levels of investment in productive capacity, hampering the growth of women-led micro, small, or medium-sized enterprises (MSMEs).&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://doi.org/10.4060/cb6966en |title=Seizing the opportunities of the African Continental Free Trade Area for the economic empowerment of women in agriculture |publisher=FAO |year=2021 |isbn=978-92-5-135021-8 |location=Accra}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alleviating financial collateral constraints can allow more women producers and traders to participate in formal markets and expand their businesses.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; According to a study conducted on women and informal cross-border trade (ICBT) in Southern Africa, women are consistently found to rely on their own personal savings and women "savings clubs" (technically, rotating savings and credit associations) to source capital for trade as opposed to commercial banks and government programmes.&lt;ref&gt;USAID, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

===Discrimination within occupations===
{{See also|Gender pay gap|Glass ceiling|Sexual harassment}}
[[File:Unemployment rate, women, OWID.svg|thumb|upright=1.6|Unemployment rate in women in 2017&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Unemployment rate, women |url=https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/unemployment-rate-women |website=Our World in Data |access-date=7 March 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The idea that men and women are naturally suited for different occupations is known as horizontal segregation.&lt;ref name="Massey"&gt;Massey, D. S. Categorically Unequal. New York: Russel Sage Foundation.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Statistical discrimination (economics)|Statistical discrimination]] in the workplace is unintentional discrimination based on the presumed probability that a worker will or will not remain with the company for a long period of time. Specific to women, employers believe that women are more likely to drop out of the labor force to have kids, or work part-time while raising kids; this tends to hurt chances for job advancement. Women are passed up for promotions because of the possibility that they may leave, and are in some cases placed in positions with little opportunity for upward mobility due to these stereotypes.&lt;ref&gt;Cabrera, E.F. Opting out and opting in: understanding the complexities of women's career transitions. Career Development International. 12, 218–237.&lt;/ref&gt;

Women typically earn less money on average than men (not accounting other variables), despite establishing equal pay laws.&lt;ref name="UNICEF-2007" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[UNICEF]], ''[http://www.unicef.org/sowc07/ State of the World's Children (2007)]'', p.&amp;nbsp;41 (Figure 3.3 "Estimated earnings for women are substantially lower than for men");p.&amp;nbsp;36 (chapter 3).&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2022 survey of 2499 adults on the state of women in the workplace, only 12% of women receive perks from their employer that could help with their finances such as student loan repayment assistance or financial counseling. Women account for two-thirds of America's trillion-dollar student debt, holding an average of $31,000 before they start their careers. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2022-03-23 |title=1 in 3 women don’t think they are being paid enough says Credello work and money survey |url=https://www.credello.com/financial-resources/trending/credello-work-and-money-survey-2022/ |access-date=2022-04-01 |website=Credello |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the textbook ''Race, Class, and Gender: An Anthology'', women are at a higher risk of financial disadvantage in modern-day society than men. Statistical findings suggest that  women are under paid for similar jobs men complete despite having the same qualifications. The statistical data collected by the U.S. Department of Labor suggests that women are discriminated against in the workforce based on gender. The textbook reads, "Women's wages are also more volatile than men's wages, and women face a much higher risk of seeing large drops in income than do men" (Kennedy 2008). Anderson clearly demonstrates a significant difference between men and women in the workforce in regards to pay. Women are left more exposed to financial devastation and unemployment. The textbook also mentions that women are often given public positions versus private or leadership positions despite having appropriate work experience, higher education, or necessary skills to qualify. According to the Joint Economic Committee, "Among women heading families, the unemployment rate has grown and is higher than the national unemployment rate and twice as high as that for either married men or married women" (Joint Economic Committee, 2009). In other words, unmarried women who are the head of household are more vulnerable to financial disadvantage than married men or women. The unemployment rate of women compared to men suggests that single women are discriminated against based on gender. Anderson writes, "All women are disproportionately at risk in the current foreclosure crisis, since women are 32% more likely than men to have subprime mortgages (One-third of women, compared to one-fourth of men, have subprime mortgages; and, the disparity between women and men increases in higher income brackets)" (Anderson 265). The statistical information illustrates the dramatic difference between men and women in regards to finances. It can be inferred that men are favored in the workforce over women. Women are discriminated against based on their gender and thus are more likely to struggle financially because of discriminatory employers.

Sex differentiation focuses on separating men and women in the workplace from different settings and duties, and it leads to the idea of [[sex segregation]].&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Women and Men at Work|last1=Reskin|first1=Barbara|last2=Padavic|first2=Irene|publisher=Pine Forge Press|year=1994|isbn=978-0-8039-9022-7|location=California|pages=[https://archive.org/details/womenmenatwork00resk/page/31 31–79]|url=https://archive.org/details/womenmenatwork00resk/page/31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Explanations for sex segregation fall under two main categories of cultural beliefs and men's efforts to preserve their advantages in the workplace. Cultural beliefs about gender and work emphasize sex stereotypes. Certain cultures value these sex stereotypes, assumptions about individuals based on sex, which leads to stereotype thinking about the genders. Jobs become labeled male or female when these sex stereotypes relate to the sexes. Cultural beliefs for sexes lays out the inequality at work women face. In Western and Eastern cultures, men are believed to be superior to women, leading to sex inequality in job duties, authority, and pay. Women are seen as requiring protection and care, and it takes away their opportunities at many jobs.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Another explanation of sex inequality is that the dominant group will preserve their position, such as men's efforts to preserve their advantages in the workplace. If women are capable of taking on the duties of male dominated jobs, especially "macho" jobs, then men's masculinity will no longer be a requirement. Women gaining equality in the workforce threatens undermining men's privileges in any other realm they wish, such as authority, family, or political life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jackson|first=Cecile|date=1999|title=Men's work, masculinities and gender divisions of labour|journal=The Journal of Development Studies.|volume=36|issue=1|pages=89–108|doi=10.1080/00220389908422613}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes the solution men choose is to try to drive the women out of the job.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

===Actions and inactions of women themselves===
Through a process known as "employee clustering", employees tend to be grouped throughout the workplace both spatially and socially with those of a similar status job. Women are no exception and tend to be grouped with other women making comparable amounts of money. They compare wages with the women around them and believe their salaries are fair because they are average. Some women are content with their lack of wage equality with men in the same positions because they are unaware of just how vast the inequality is.

Furthermore, women as a whole tend to be less assertive and confrontational. One of the factors contributing to the higher proportion of raises going to men is the simple fact that men tend to ask for raises more often than women, and are more aggressive when doing so.&lt;ref name="women's media"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.womensmedia.com|title=Index of /|publisher=Womensmedia.com|access-date=17 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women, and men, are socialized at young ages into these roles. School-age boys and girls have been noted as enacting the same aggressive and passive characteristics, respectively, in educational settings that we see in adults in the workplace. Boys are more likely to be pushed competitively in school, and sports, to be dominant. The idea that "winning is everything" is not emphasized to the same extent for girls and therefore they are less likely to seek recognition for their work.&lt;ref&gt;Spade, Joan Z. "Gender and Education in the US." Gender Mosaics: Social Perspectives. Ed. Dana VannoyOxford University Press, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

An additional issue that contributes to income inequality by gender is that women are much more likely than men to take "breaks" in their careers to have children, often remaining out of the workforce for extended periods of time, while men in the same role or occupation (or other women who do not leave the workforce) most likely are continuing to earn promotions and/or merit-based salary increases. When a woman in this scenario re-enters the workforce, she may be offered a smaller salary or a lower position than she might have merited had she remained in the workforce alongside her colleagues (both male and female) who have not interrupted their careers.

=== Sex segregation ===
[[File:Abeer Mostafa at work.jpg|thumb|An Egyptian Muslim woman who works in a men's hairdresser. She described to be "confront the customs and traditions of her society and conquer their criticism."]]
A form of discrimination in the workplace is sex segregation. Men and women are separated to do different tasks, same tasks in different settings or at different times. Historically, most men did agricultural work while women managed the household, however within time women eased their way into employment, but the segregation they experience remained. Males identify with the masculine identity and their authority are considered appropriate. Male dominated industries do not leave a chance for women to prove possible history in the role, leaving the job identified as a male way of working.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Little|first=Jo|date=2002|title=Rural geography: rural gender identity and the performance of masculinity and femininity in the countryside|journal=Progress in Human Geography|volume=26|issue=5|pages=665–670|doi=10.1191/0309132502ph394pr|s2cid=143209872}}&lt;/ref&gt; Males masculine behavior undermine females in the workforce, and they are forced to endure it. Women's segregation in the workforce takes form of normative masculine cultural dominance. Men put on the image of macho physical toughness, limiting women in their careers. Women find themselves experiencing the concept of "doing gender", especially in a traditional masculine occupation. Women's standpoint of men's behavior sheds light on mobilizing masculinity. With the feminist standpoint view of gender in the workplace, men's gender is an advantage, whereas women's is a handicap.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Martin|first=Patricia|date=2001|title='Mobilizing Masculinities': Women's Experiences of Men at Work".|journal=Organization Articles|volume=8|issue=4|pages=587–618|doi=10.1177/135050840184003|s2cid=144973890}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Watts|first=Jacqueline|date=2007|title=Porn, pride, and pessimism: experiences of women working in professional construction roles|journal=Work, Employment and Society|volume=21|issue=2|pages=299–316|doi=10.1177/0950017007076641|s2cid=143014014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, sex segregation can happen by women's and men's own choices of different occupations.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Descriptive gender stereotypes emphasize the characteristics a woman possesses. The prescriptive component focuses on the beliefs about characteristics a woman should possess. The descriptive component is expected to lead to workplace discrimination, while the prescriptive component is expected to lead to discrimination against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |doi = 10.1037/1076-8971.5.3.665|title = Who women are, who women should be: Descriptive and prescriptive gender stereotyping in sex discrimination|journal = Psychology, Public Policy, and Law|volume = 5|issue = 3|pages = 665–692|year = 1999|last1 = Burgess|first1 = Diana|last2 = Borgida|first2 = Eugene}}&lt;/ref&gt; If women violate these prescriptions, they are more susceptible to disparate treatment. In other words, if a woman is able to perform a job that generally requires stereotypical male masculinity they receive the discrimination that punishes women for violating the prescriptions of feminine characteristics.

==Gender inequality by social class==
[[File:Mechanic at work seattle.jpg|thumb|upright|Mechanic working on a motorcycle, United States]]
In the last 50 years, there have been great changes toward gender equality in industrialized nations, such as the United States of America. With the [[feminist movement]] of the 1960s, women began to enter the workforce in great numbers. Women also had high labor market participation during World]]s. In the late 1960s when women began entering the labor force in record numbers, they were entering in addition to all of the men, as opposed to substituting for men during the war. This dynamic shift from the one-earner household to the two-earner household dramatically changed the socioeconomic class system of industrialized nations in the post-war period.

===Effects on the middle and upper classes===
The addition of women into the workforce was one of the key factors that has increased [[social mobility]] over the last 50 years, although this has stalled in recent decades for both genders. Female children of the middle and upper classes had increased access to higher education, and thanks to job equality, were able to attain higher-paying and higher-prestige jobs than ever before. Due to the dramatic increase in availability of [[birth control]], these high status women were able to delay marriage and child-bearing until they had completed their education and advanced their careers to their desired positions. In 2001, the survey on sexual harassment at workplace conducted by women's non-profit organisation Sakshi among 2,410 respondents in government and non-government sectors, in five states{{clarify|date=December 2018|reason=United States?}}{{citation needed|date=December 2018}} recorded 53 percent saying that both sexes don't get equal opportunities, 50 percent of women are treated unfairly by employers and co-workers, 59 per cent have heard sexist remarks or jokes, and 32 percent have been exposed to pornography or literature degrading women.

In comparison with other sectors, IT organisations may be offering equal salaries to women, and the density of women in technology companies may be relatively high, but this does not necessarily ensure a level playing field. For example, Microsoft (US) was sued because of the conduct of one of its supervisors over e-mail. The supervisor allegedly made sexually offensive comments via e-mail, such as referring to himself as "president of the amateur gynecology club". He also allegedly referred to the plaintiff as the "Spandex Queen". E-harassment is not the sole form of harassment. In 1999, Juno Online faced two separate suits from former employees who alleged that they were told that they would be fired if they broke off their ongoing relationships with senior executives. Pseudo Programs, a Manhattan-based Internet TV network, was sued in January 2000 after male employees referred to female employees as "bimbos" and forced them to look at sexually explicit material on the Internet. In India, HR managers admit that women are discriminated against for senior Board positions and pregnant women are rarely given jobs but only in private. In addition to this, it has been suggested that there are fewer women in the IT sector due to existing stereotypes that depict the sector as male-orientated. In a recent book, ''Own It: Leadership Lessons From Women Who Do'', author [[Aparna Jain]] interviewed 200 women in senior management and leadership positions in India about the problems they face at the workplace and noted that 86% of the women she spoke to experienced harassment in one form or the other.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/books/towards-fostering-a-gender-neutral-workplace/story-32TrlU2iOhQfWGGWStcSYL.html | title=Finally, a book that talks about gender-neutral workplace| date=2016-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the issues she notes are bias, bullying, sexual harassment and the impact of motherhood on women's career.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.firstpost.com/living/book-review-aparna-jains-own-it-brings-out-of-unarticulated-darkness-the-indescribable-things-that-happen-to-women-at-the-workplace-2614092.html |title = Book Review: Aparna Jain's 'Own It' brings out of unarticulated darkness the indescribable things that happen to women at the workplace}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recently a sexual harassment suit against a senior member shocked the Indian IT sector, as was the sexual harassment case against the [[Taj Hotels Resorts and Palaces]]' (Taj Group) CEO, Rakesh Sarna .&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | url=http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/company/corporate-trends/sexual-harassment-case-against-ihcl-boss-rakesh-sarna-may-have-added-to-cyrus-mistry-woes/articleshow/55361051.cms | title=Sexual harassment case against Taj CEO Rakesh Sarna made it tougher for Cyrus Mistry| newspaper=The Economic Times| date=2019-05-29| last1=Barman| first1=Arijit| last2=Mahanta| first2=Vinod| last3=Vijayraghavan| first3=Kala}}&lt;/ref&gt; A startling example of institutional mechanisms that allow for an unfettered environment for sexual harassment to fester is the [[Rajendra K. Pachauri]] scandal at [[The Energy and Resources Institute]] in India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.caravanmagazine.in/reportage/hostile-climate-rk-pachauri-reign-teri | title=RK Pachauri's reign at TERI}}&lt;/ref&gt; Improvements in the education system could be the key to encouraging women to take up roles in this sector.

Recognizing the invisible nature of power structures that marginalize women at the workplace, the Supreme Court in the landmark case ''Vaishaka versus High Court of Rajasthan'' (1997) identified sexual harassment as violative of the women's right to equality in the workplace and enlarged the ambit of its definition. The judgment equates a [[hostile work environment]] on the same plane as a direct request for sexual favors. To quote: "Sexual harassment includes such unwelcome sexually determined behaviour (whether directly or by implication) as: physical contact and advances; a demand or request for sexual favours; sexually coloured remarks; showing pornography; any other unwelcome physical, verbal or non-verbal conduct of sexual nature". The judgement mandates appropriate work conditions should be provided for work, leisure, health, and hygiene to further ensure that there is no hostile environment towards women at the workplace and no woman employee should have reasonable grounds to believe that she is disadvantaged in connection with her employment.

This law thus squarely shifts the onus onto the employer to ensure employee safety but most mid-sized Indian service technology companies are yet to enact sexual harassment policies. Admits K Chandan, an advocate from Chandan Associates, "I have a few IT clients. When I point to the need for a sexual harassment policy, most tend to overlook or ignore it. It's not high on the agenda." An HR Manager of India's premier technology companies rues: "I am going to use the recent case to push the policy through. Earlier the draft proposal was rejected by the company." Yet another HR manager from a flagship company of India's leading business house, oblivious to the irony of her statement, admitted that the company had a grievance redressal mechanism but no sexual harassment policy in place. The lax attitudes transgress the Supreme Court judgment wherein the Court not only defined sexual harassment, but also laid down a code of conduct for workplaces to prevent and punish it, "Employers or other responsible authorities in public or private sectors must comply with the following guidelines: Express prohibition of sexual harassment should be notified and circulated; private employers should include prohibition of sexual harassment in the standing orders under the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946." As for the complaint procedure, not less than half of its members should be women. The complaint committee should include an NGO or other organization that is familiar with the issue of sexual harassment. When the offense amounts to misconduct under service rules, appropriate disciplinary action should be initiated. When such conduct amounts to an offense under the Indian Penal Code, the employer shall initiate action by making a complaint with the appropriate authority. However, the survey by Sakshi revealed 58 per cent of women were not aware of the Supreme Court guidelines on the subject. A random survey by AssureConsulting.com among hundred employees working in the IT industry revealed startling results: Less than 10 per cent were familiar with the law or the company's sexual harassment policy. Surprisingly, certain HR managers were also ignorant of the Supreme Court guidelines or the Draft Bill by the National Commission of Women against sexual harassment at the workplace.

Not surprisingly many cases go unreported. However, given the complexities involved, company policy is the first step and cannot wish away the problem. Says Savita HR Manager at Icelerate Technologies, "We have a sexual harassment policy that is circulated among employees. Also the company will not tolerate any case that comes to its notice. But the man at home is no different from the person at the office", thus implying the social mindset that discriminates against women is responsible for the problem. Considering sexual censorship and conservative social attitudes emphasizing "woman's purity", the victim dare not draw attention for fear of being branded a woman with "loose morals". Women would rather brush away the problem or leave jobs quietly rather than speak up, even in organizations that have a zero tolerance policy. Says Chandan, "I do not have exact statistics but from my experience as an advocate one in 1,500 cases are reported." The problem cannot be resolved till more women speak up but the social set-up browbeats women into silence. The social stigma against the victim and the prolonged litigation process for justice thwarts most women from raising their voice. Purports K Chandan "It may take between three and five years to settle a case, and in a situation where the harassment is covert, evidence is hard to gather and there is no guarantee that the ruling would be in favour of the victim. In one of the rare cases I handled a Country Manager was accused and the plaintiff opted for an out of court settlement."

===Effects on the working class===
Women in lower wage jobs are more likely to be subject to wage discrimination. They are more likely to bring home far less than their male counterparts with equal job status, and get far less help with housework from their husbands than the high-earning women. Women with low educational attainment entering the workforce in mass quantity lowered earnings for some men, as the women brought about a lot more job competition. The lowered relative earnings of the men and increase in birth control made marriage prospects harder for lower income women.&lt;ref&gt;Edin, K. and Kefalas, M. (2005). ''Promises I Can Keep: Why poor women put motherhood before marriage''. Berkeley, California: University of California Press&lt;/ref&gt;

For the first time in the history of this country,{{which|date=January 2014}} there were distinctive socioeconomic stratification among women as there has been among men for centuries. This deepened the inequality between the upper/middle and lower/working classes. Prior to the feminist movement, the socioeconomic status of a family was based almost solely on the husband/father's occupation. Women who were now attaining high status jobs were attractive partners to men with high status jobs, so the high earners married the high earners and the low earners married the low earners. In other words, the rich got richer and the poor stayed the same, and have had increased difficulty competing in the economy.&lt;ref name="Massey" /&gt;

==Impact issues of female participation in the workforce==
A 2008 study published in the ''[[British Medical Journal]]'' found that women were 46% more likely to call in sick for short time periods than men and a third more likely than men to take short term sick leave. At 60 days or more, men and women were equal in terms of sick leave.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|via=[[Science Daily]]|url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2008/02/080204212846.htm|title=Women Take Almost 50 Percent More Short-term Sick Leave Than Men|work=[[BMJ]]|date=5 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of women in the workforce has tripled and due to this increase, it has become difficult for both mothers and fathers to be able to take care of their own new born child or a sick family member. The [[Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993]] has allowed for workers to have up to 12 weeks a year to leave work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Scharlach A. E. |author2=Grosswald B. | year = 1997 | title = The Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 | journal = Social Service Review | volume = 71 | issue = 3| pages = 335–359 | doi=10.1086/604261|s2cid=33188704 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Female labor and the pill ===
Women have for a long time been unable to actively participate in the labor force. One main reason is the lack of freedom as to when to have kids. With the advancement of the contraceptive pill in the US and nonstop women activists like Katherine Mccormick,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Connell|first=Elizabeth B.|date=1999-01-01|title=Contraception in the prepill era|url=https://www.contraceptionjournal.org/article/S0010-7824(98)00130-9/abstract|journal=Contraception|language=English|volume=59|issue=1|pages=7S–10S|doi=10.1016/S0010-7824(98)00130-9|issn=0010-7824}}&lt;/ref&gt; women gained access to the pill in the 1960s, and with time wild access has been made available for women all over the world. Now women have the option to control when they want to have kids and have more power over their life plans. This might seem like women were the most affected by this change. However, the pill also changed the game for men. In his article about the pill, Rob Norton&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Sex, Drugs, and Career Choices When young women first got access to the birth control pill in the late 1960s, their career options--and the future shape of the U.S. work force--changed completely. - April 3, 2000|url=https://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2000/04/03/277097/index.htm|access-date=2021-12-14|website=money.cnn.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; mentioned the impact it had on couples as a whole. We have two effects related to the universality of the pill. The Direct effect is how it affected the educational and career path of most women. For instance, women were able to postpone when they wanted to have kids and focus on their education and career advancement. We also have the indirect effect which shows how it impacted both men and women as to when they wanted to get married or start a family. Both partners now had the ability to focus on theirs careers and personal advancement without being worried of not finding any eligible bachelor later on.

==== Lack of family-friendly policies in the workplace ====
Since the 2000s, there has been a decrease in the female labor participation rate in the US partly because the lack of family-friendly workplace. For example, The U.S does not have any [[paid maternity leave]] although other countries over the world have been making tremendous progress in this area. In Ireland, paid maternity leave is 26 weeks, and in China, it is 14 weeks. Women in the US are more likely to access higher positions in companies than in those other countries because they spend less time on maternity leave, which offers them a competitive advantage. However,the lack of family-friendly policiesgreatly harms the mother's mental health and sometimes the baby, which explains the decrease in female labor participation. Lastly, men also get affected by this lack of family-friendly policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Kinlin|first=Ellen|date=2017-05-30|title=Women and Men Declining in the Workforce|url=https://www.kinlin.com/women-men-declining-workforce/|access-date=2021-12-14|website=The Kinlin Company|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fertility===
Increased participation of women in the workforce is associated with decreased fertility. A cross-country panel study found this [[fertility factor (demography)|fertility factor]] effect to be strongest among women aged 20–39, but with a less strong but persistent effect among older women as well.&lt;ref name=bloom2007&gt;{{cite journal |first1=David |last1=Bloom |first2=David |last2=Canning |first3=Günther |last3=Fink |first4=Jocelyn |last4=Finlay |year=2009 |title=Fertility, female labor force participation, and the demographic dividend |journal=[[Journal of Economic Growth]] |volume=14 |issue=2 |pages=79–101 |doi=10.1007/s10887-009-9039-9 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; International [[United Nations]] data suggests that women who work because of economic necessity have higher fertility than those who work because they want to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/esa/population/publications/completingfertility/RevisedLIMpaper.PDF|title=Female Labour-Force Participation|author=Lin Lean Lim|publisher=[[United Nations]]}}, part of {{cite book|title=Completing the Fertility Transition|year=2009|publisher=[[United Nations]] Publications|isbn=9789211513707}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The impact of women's employment is more negatively associated with the birth of a second child, as opposed to the first&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Matysiak|first1=Anna|last2=Vignoli|first2=Daniele|date=2013|title=Diverse Effects of Women's Employment on Fertility: Insights From Italy and Poland|journal=European Journal of Population|volume=29|issue=3|pages=273–302|doi=10.1007/s10680-013-9287-4|issn=0168-6577|pmc=3744382|pmid=23956480}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, for countries in the [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development|OECD]] area, increased female labor participation has been associated with an increased fertility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=A Note on the Changing Relationship between Fertility and Female Employment Rates in Developed Countries|author1=Namkee Ahn  |author2=Pedro Mira |name-list-style=amp |journal=Journal of Population Economics|volume=15|issue=4|year=2002|pages=667–682|jstor=20007839 |doi=10.1007/s001480100078|s2cid=17755082 |url=http://documentos.fedea.net/pubs/eee/eee13.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Causality analyses indicate that fertility rate influences female labor participation and not as much the other way around.&lt;ref name=balbo2013/&gt;

Regarding types of jobs, women who work in nurturing professions such as teaching and health generally have children at an earlier age.&lt;ref name=balbo2013/&gt; It is theorized that women often self-select themselves into jobs with a favorable [[work–life balance]] in order to combine motherhood and employment.&lt;ref name=balbo2013&gt;{{cite journal|title=Fertility in Advanced Societies: A Review of Research|author1=Nicoletta Balbo |author2=Francesco C. Billari |author3=Melinda Mills |journal=European Journal of Population|year=2013|volume=29|issue=1 |doi=10.1007/s10680-012-9277-y |pages=1–38 |pmid=23440941 |pmc=3576563}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Globalize|section|US|date=June 2020}}

===19th century===
Women have worked at agricultural tasks since ancient times, and continue to do so around the world. The [[Industrial Revolution]] of the late 18th and early 19th centuries changed the nature of work in Europe and other countries of the Western world. Working for a [[wage]], and eventually a [[salary]], became part of urban life. Initially, women were to be found doing even the hardest physical labor, including working as "hurriers" hauling heavy coal carts through mine shafts in Great Britain, a job that also employed many children. This ended after government intervention and the passing of the [[Mines and Collieries Act 1842]], an early attempt at regulating the workplace.

During the 19th century, an increasing number of women in Western countries took jobs in factories, such as textile mills, or on assembly lines for machinery or other goods. Women also worked as "[[hawker (trade)|hawker]]s" of produce, flowers, and other market goods, and bred small animals in the working-class areas of London. [[Piecework]], which involved needlework (weaving, embroidery, winding wool or silk) that paid by the piece completed, was the most common employment for women in 19th century Great Britain. It was poorly paid, and involved long hours, up to 14 hours per day to earn enough wages to survive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Perkin|first=Joan|title=Victorian Women|year=1993|publisher=John Murray (Publishers) Ltd.|location=London|isbn=978-0-7195-4955-7|pages=189}}&lt;/ref&gt; Working-class women were usually involved in some form of paid employment, as it provided some insurance against the possibility that their husband might become too ill or injured to support the family. During the era before [[workers' compensation]] for disability or illness, the loss of a husband's wages could result in the entire family being sent to a Victorian [[workhouse]] to pay debts.

Inequality in wages was to be expected for women. In 1906, the government found that the average weekly factory wage for a woman ranged from 11s 3d to 18s 8d, whereas a man's average weekly wage was around 25s 9d. Employers stated they preferred to hire women, because they could be "more easily induced to undergo severe bodily fatigue than men".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Perkin|first=Joan|title=Victorian Women|year=1993|publisher=John Murray (Publishers) Ltd.|location=London|isbn=978-0-7195-4955-7|pages=191}}&lt;/ref&gt; Childminding was another necessary expense for many women working in factories. Pregnant women worked up until the day they gave birth and returned to work as soon as they were physically able. In 1891, a law was passed requiring women to take four weeks away from factory work after giving birth, but many women could not afford this unpaid leave, and the law was unenforceable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Perkin|first=Joan|title=Victorian Women|year=1993|publisher=John Murray (Publishers) Ltd.|location=London|isbn=978-0-7195-4955-7|pages=192–3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[1870 US Census]] was the first United States Census to count "females engaged in each occupation" and provides an intriguing snapshot of women's history. It reveals that, contrary to popular belief, not all American women of the 19th century were either idle in their middle-class homes or working in [[sweatshop]]s. Women were 15% of the total work force (1.8&amp;nbsp;million out of 12.5). They made up one-third of factory "operatives", but teaching and the occupations of [[dressmaking]], [[Hatmaking|millinery]], and [[tailoring]] played a larger role. Two-thirds of teachers were women. Women could also be found in such unexpected places as iron and steel works (495), mines (46), sawmills (35), oil wells and refineries (40), gas works (4), and charcoal kilns (5) and held such surprising jobs as ship rigger (16), teamster (196), turpentine laborer (185), brass founder/worker (102), shingle and lathe maker (84), stock-herder (45), gun and locksmith (33), and hunter and trapper (2).  Formal classification may grossly under-estimate female labor force participation via self-employment or family employment with studies suggesting participation may have always been high.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Chiswick |first1=Barry R. |last2=Robinson |first2=RaeAnn Halenda |title=Women at Work in the United States Since 1860: An Analysis of Unreported Family Workers |journal=Explorations in Economic History |date=8 June 2021 |volume=82 |page=101406 |doi=10.1016/j.eeh.2021.101406 |s2cid=236223225 |url=https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0014498321000243 |access-date=17 June 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===20th century===
[[File:We Can Do It! NARA 535413 - Restoration 2.jpg|thumb|right|upright|In the United States, the "[[Rosie the Riveter]]" image, as it has become known, is an iconic representation of the US government's efforts to exhort women to work during World War II, and has been adapted numerous times to represent working women or, more broadly, women overcoming adversity and other [[proto-feminist]] messages.]]

In the beginning of the 20th century, women were regarded as society's guardians of morality; they were seen as possessing a finer nature than men and were expected to act as such.&lt;ref name="Davis, R.L p.10"&gt;Davis, R. L: "The Social and Cultural Life of the 1920s", p.10. Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc., 1972,&lt;/ref&gt; Their role was not defined as workers or money makers. Women were expected to hold on to their innocence until the right man came along so that they can start a family and inculcate that morality they were in charge of preserving. The role of men was to support the family financially.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, R. L: "The Social and Cultural Life of the 1920s", p. 9. Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc. 1972.&lt;/ref&gt; Yet at the turn of the 20th century, social attitudes towards educating young women were changing. Women in North America and Western Europe were now becoming more and more educated, in no small part because of the efforts of pioneering women to further their own education, defying opposition by male educators. By 1900, four out of five colleges accepted women and a whole coed concept was becoming more and more accepted.&lt;ref&gt;Walker, R. H: "Life in the Age of Enterprise", pp. 120-121. Capricorn Books, 1971.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:The Arms Production in Britain in the First World War Q27868.jpg|thumb|left|Working at the Woolwich Arsenal, London, United Kingdom, 1918]]

In the United States, World War I made space for women in the workforce, among other economical and social influences. Due to the rise in demand for production from Europe during the raging war, more women found themselves working outside the home.

In the first quarter of the century, women mostly occupied jobs in factory work or as domestic servants, but as the war came to an end they were able to move on to such jobs as: salespeople in department stores as well as clerical, secretarial and other, what were called, "lace-collar" jobs.&lt;ref name="Green-57"&gt;Green, E: "The Uncertainty of Everyday Life, 1915–1945", pp. 57-58. HarperCollins, 1992,&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1920, [[The New York Times]] ran a head line that read: "the American Woman ... has lifted her skirts far beyond any modest limitation"&lt;ref name="Davis, R.L p.10" /&gt; which could apply to more than just fashion; women were now rolling up their sleeves and skirts and making their way into the workforce.

World War II created millions of jobs for women. Thousands of American women actually joined the military:
140,000 in the [[Women's Army Corps (United States Army)]] WAC;
100,000 in the Navy (WAVE);
23,000 in the Marines;
14,000 in the [[Navy Nurse Corps]] and,
13,000 in the Coast Guard. Although almost none saw combat, they replaced men in noncombat positions and got the same pay as the men would have on the same job. At the same time over 16&amp;nbsp;million men left their jobs to join the war in Europe and elsewhere, opening even more opportunities and places for women to take over in the job force.&lt;ref name="Green-57"/&gt; Although two million women lost their jobs after the war ended, female participation in the workforce was still higher than it had ever been.&lt;ref name=Moody1998&gt;{{cite book|last=Moody|first=Kim|author-link=Kim Moody|title=An injury to all : the decline of American Unionism|year=1988|publisher=Verso|location=London|page=22|isbn=978-0860919292|quote=The rate of participation of women in the labor force rose from about 28% in 1940 to 37% in 1945 and then fell to 30% in 1947. By 1950, it was around 32%, below the wartime peak but above the prewar level.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In post-war America, women were expected to return to private life as homemakers and child-rearers. Newspapers and magazines directed at women encouraged them to keep a tidy home while their husbands were away at work. These articles presented the home as a woman's proper domain, which she was expected to run.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Roche | first = Mary| title =A House for Mother| newspaper = The New York Times| date = 22 May 1949 | url = https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1949/05/22/issue.html|page=240| access-date = 8 May 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Homeward Bound: American Families in the Cold War Era|last=May|first=Elaine Tyler|publisher=Basic Books|year=1988|pages=10–29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, jobs were still available to women. However, they were mostly what are known as "[[Pink-collar worker|pink-collar]]" jobs such as retail clerks and secretaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Classified ad 15 -- no title|date=Oct 26, 1947|work=New York Times|id={{ProQuest|108065674}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; The propaganda to encourage women to return to the home is depicted in the film ''[[The Life and Times of Rosie the Riveter]]''.

===The Quiet Revolution===
[[File:Customer account operators seattle.gif|thumb|Customer account operators working for a large photography firm, United States, 1945]]
[[File:Waitress diner pike place seattle.gif|thumb|A woman working as wait staff at a diner, United States, 1981]]
The increase of women in the labor force of Western countries gained momentum in the late 19th century. At this point women married early on and were defined by their marriages. If they entered the workforce, it was only out of necessity.

The first phase encompasses the time between the late 19th century to the 1930s. This era gave birth to the "independent female worker". From 1890 to 1930, women in the workforce were typically young and unmarried. They had little or no learning on the job and typically held clerical and teaching positions. Many women also worked in textile manufacturing or as domestics. Women promptly exited the work force when they were married, unless the family needed two incomes. Towards the end of the 1920s, as we enter into the second phase, married women begin to exit the work force less and less. Labor force productivity for married women 35–44 years of age increase by 15.5 percentage points from 10% to 25%. There was a greater demand for clerical positions and as the number of women graduating high school increased they began to hold more "respectable", steady jobs. This phase has been appropriately labeled as the Transition Era referring to the time period between 1930 and 1950. During this time the discriminatory institution of [[marriage bars]], which forced women out of the work force after marriage, were eliminated, allowing more participation in the work force of single and married women. Additionally, women's labor force participation increased because there was an increase in demand for office workers and women participated in the high school movement. However, still women's work was contingent upon their husband's income. Women did not normally work to fulfill a personal need to define ones career and social worth; they worked out of necessity.

In the third phase, labeled the "roots of the revolution" encompassing the time from 1950– mid-to-late 1970s, the movement began to approach the warning signs of a revolution. Women's expectations of future employment changed. Women began to see themselves going on to college and working through their marriages and even attending graduate school. Many however still had brief and intermittent work force participation, without necessarily having expectations for a "career". To illustrate, most women were secondary earners, and worked in "pink-collar jobs" as secretaries, teachers, nurses, and librarians. The [[sexual harassment]] experienced by these [[Pink-collar worker|pink collar]] workers is depicted in the film ''[[9 to 5 (film)|9 to 5]]''. Although more women attended college, it was often expected that they attended to find a spouse—the so-called "M.R.S. degree". Nevertheless, Labor force participation by women still grew significantly.

The fourth phase, known as the "Quiet Revolution", began in the late 1970s and continues on today. Beginning in the 1970s women began to flood colleges and grad schools. They began to enter profession like [[women in medicine|medicine]], law, dental and business. More women were going to college and expected to be employed at the age of 35, as opposed to past generations that only worked intermittently due to marriage and childbirth. They were able to define themselves prior to a serious relationship. Research indicates that from 1965 to 2002, the increase in women's labor force participation more than offset the decline for men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagofed.org/digital_assets/publications/working_papers/2003/wp2003-22.pdf|publisher=Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago|title=''Do Women's and Men's Labor Market Outcomes Differentially Affect Real Wage Growth and Inflation?''|date=November 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The reasons for this big jump in the 1970s has been attributed by some scholars to widespread access to the [[birth control pill]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last1= Bailey| first1= Martha| date = February 2006| title= More Power to the Pill: The Impact of Contraceptive Freedom on Women's Life Cycle Labor Supply| url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/25098791| journal = The Quarterly Journal of Economics| volume = 121| issue = 1| pages = 289–320| jstor= 25098791| access-date = 11 May 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; While "the pill" was medically available in the 1960s, numerous laws restricted access to it. See, e.g., ''[[Griswold v. Connecticut]]'', 381 U.S. 479 (1965) (overturning a Connecticut statute barring access to contraceptives) and ''[[Eisenstadt v. Baird]]'', 405 U.S. 438 (1972) (establishing the right of unmarried people to access contraception). By the 1970s, the [[age of majority]] had been lowered from 21 to 18 in the United States, largely as a consequence of the [[Vietnam War]]; this also affected women's right to effect their own medical decisions. Since it had now become socially acceptable to postpone pregnancy even while married, women had the luxury of thinking about other things, like education and work. Also, due to electrification women's work around the house became easier leaving them with more time to be able to dedicate to school or work. Due to the multiplier effect, even if some women were not blessed with access to the pill or electrification, many followed by the example of the other women entering the work force for those reasons. The Quiet Revolution is called such because it was not a "big bang" revolution; rather, it happened and is continuing to happen gradually.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Goldin, Claudia | title = The Quiet Revolution That Transformed Women's Employment, Education and Family | journal = The American Economic Review | volume = 96 | issue = 2 | date = 2006 | pages = 1–21 | doi=10.1257/000282806777212350| url = http://www.nber.org/papers/w11953.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Occupational safety and health ==
Women tend to have different occupational hazards and health issues than men in the workplace. Women get [[carpal tunnel syndrome]], [[tendonitis]], [[anxiety disorder]]s, [[stress (psychological)|stress]], respiratory diseases, and infectious diseases due to their work at higher rates than men. The reasons for these differences may be differences in biology or in the work that women are performing. Women's higher rates of job-related stress may be due to the fact that women are often [[caregiver]]s at home and do [[contingent work]] and [[contract work]] at a much higher rate than men. Another significant occupational hazard for women is [[homicide]], which was the second most frequent cause of death on the job for women in 2011, making up 26% of workplace deaths in women.&lt;ref name=NIOSH&gt;{{cite web |url = http://blogs.cdc.gov/niosh-science-blog/2013/05/13/womens-health-at-work/ |title = Women's Health at Work |publisher = National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health |access-date = 21 January 2015 |date = 13 May 2013 |first1 = Naomi |last1 = Swanson |first2 = Julie |last2 = Tisdale-Pardi |first3 = Leslie |last3 = MacDonald |first4 = Hope M. |last4 = Tiesman}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/women/#2|title = Women's Safety and Health Issues at Work|date = June 19, 2013|publisher = NIOSH}}&lt;/ref&gt; Immigrant women are at higher risk for occupational injury than native-born women in the United States, due to higher rates of employment in dangerous industries.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Women are at lower risk for work-related death than men. However, [[personal protective equipment]] is usually designed for typical male proportions, which can create hazards for women who have ill-fitting equipment.&lt;ref name=NIOSH/&gt; Women are less likely to report an occupational injury than men.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Research is ongoing into occupational hazards that may be specific to women. Of particular interest are potential [[Toxic substance|environmental causes]] of [[breast cancer]] and [[cervical cancer]].&lt;ref name=NIOSH/&gt; [[Sexual harassment]] is an occupational hazard for many women, and can cause serious negative symptoms including [[anxiety]], [[Depression (mood)|depression]], [[nausea]], [[headache]], [[insomnia]], and feelings of low self-esteem and alienation. Women are also at higher risk for [[occupational stress]], which can be caused by balancing roles as a parent or caregiver with work.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==See also==
*[[Feminisation of the workplace]]
*[[Rosie the Riveter]]
*[[Employment discrimination]]
*[[Occupational sexism]]
*[[Motherhood penalty]]

===Women's participation in different occupations===
[[File:Beata Chmielowska-Olech beax.jpg|thumb|A news anchor going live on TV in Poland]]
Below is a sample of encyclopedia articles that detail women's historical involvement in various occupations.
*[[Women in science]]
**[[Women in computing]]
**[[Women in engineering]]
**[[Women in geology]]
*[[Women in medicine]]

*Arts, writing, media, sports and entertainment
**[[Women artists]] (visual arts)
**Writing
***[[Women's writing (literary category)]]
***[[Women in journalism]]
**Film
***[[Women's cinema]] (discusses women screenwriters &amp; directors)
**Sports
***[[Women's professional sports]]
*[[Women in government]]
*[[Women in the military]]

== Source ==

{{Free-content attribution
| title = Seizing the opportunities of the African Continental Free Trade Area for the economic empowerment of women in agriculture
| author = FAO
| publisher = FAO
| page numbers = 
| source = 
| documentURL = https://doi.org/10.4060/cb6966en
| license statement URL = https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Seizing_the_opportunities_of_the_African_Continental_Free_Trade_Area_for_the_economic_empowerment_of_women_in_agriculture.pdf
| license = CC BY-SA 3.0
}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{Further reading cleanup|date=February 2021}}
;History of women in workforce
*''A Woman's Wage: Historical Meanings and Social Consequences'' by Alice Kessler-Harris (updated edition, 2014)
*''Challenging Professions: Historical and Contemporary Perspectives on Women's Professional Work'' by Elizabeth Smyth, Sandra Acker, [[Paula Bourne]], and Alison Prentice (1999)
*''English women enter the professions'' by Nellie Alden Franz (1965)
*''Black Women and White Women in the Professions: Occupational Segregation by Race and Gender, 1960–1980'' (Perspectives on Gender) by N. Sokoloff (1992)
*''Unequal Colleagues: The Entrance of Women into the Professions, 1890–1940'' (Douglass Series on Women's Lives and the Meaning of Gender) by Penina Migdal Glazer and Miriam Slater (1987)
*''Beyond Her Sphere: Women and the Professions in American History''  by Barbara J. Harris (1978)
*"Challenging Professions: Historical and Contemporary Perspectives on Women's Professional Work" (Book Reviews) Pamela Sugiman in ''Relations Industrielles/Industrial Relations''
*''Victorian Working Women: A historical and literary study of women in British industries and professions 1832–1850'' (Economic History (Routledge)) by Wanda F. Neff
*''Colonial women of affairs;: A study of women in business and the professions in America before 1776'' by Elisabeth Anthony Dexter
*''What a Woman Ought to Be and to Do: Black Professional Women Workers during the Jim Crow Era'' (Women in Culture and Society Series)  by Stephanie J. Shaw
*'' In Subordination: Professional Women, 1870–1970'' by Mary Kinnear (1995)
*''Women Working in Nontraditional Fields References and Resources 1963–1988'' (Women's Studies Series)  by Carroll Wetzel Wilkinson
* {{cite book |last=Kinnear |first=Karen L. |title=Women in Developing Countries: a Reference Handbook |publisher=ABC-Clio |year=2011 |isbn=9781598844252}}

;Social sciences and psychological perspectives;
*Suhail Ahmad, ''Women in profession: A comparative study of Hindu and Muslim women''
*Ella L. J. Edmondson Bell and Stella M. Nkomo, ''Our Separate Ways: Black and White Women and the Struggle for Professional Identity''
*Julia Evetts, ''Women and Career: Themes and Issues in Advanced Industrial Societies'' (Longman Sociology Series)
*Patricia N. Feulner, ''Women in the Professions: A Social-Psychological Study''
*Linda S. Fidell and [[John D. DeLamater]], ''Women in the Professions''
*Clara Greed, ''Surveying Sisters: Women in a Traditional Male Profession''
*Jerry Jacobs, ''Professional Women at Work: Interactions, Tacit Understandings, and the Non-Trivial Nature of Trivia in Bureaucratic Settings''
*[[Edith Morley|Edith J. Morley]], ''Women Workers in Seven Professions''
*Xiomara Santamarina, ''Belabored Professions: Narratives of African American Working Womanhood''
*Janet Skarbek, ''Planning Your Future: A Guide for Professional Women''
*Elizabeth Smyth, Sandra Acker, Paula Bourne, and Alison Prentice, ''Challenging Professions: Historical and Contemporary Perspectives on Women's Professional Work''
*Nancy C. Talley-Ross, ''Jagged Edges: Black Professional Women in White Male Worlds'' (Studies in African and African-American Culture, Vol 7) (1995)
*Joyce Tang and Earl Smith, ''Women and Minorities in American Professions'' (S U N Y Series on the New Inequalities)
*{{cite journal | author = Anne Witz | title = Patriarchy and Professions: The Gendered Politics of Occupational Closure | journal = Sociology | volume = 24 | issue = 4 | date = 1990 | pages = 675–690 | doi = 10.1177/0038038590024004007 | s2cid = 143826607 }}
*Anne Witz, ''Professions and Patriarchy'' (International Library of Sociology)  (1992)

;Work and family demands/support for women
*Terri Apter, ''Working Women Don't Have Wives: Professional Success in the 1990s''
*Sian Griffiths, ''Beyond the Glass Ceiling: Forty Women Whose Ideas Shape the Modern World'' (Women's Studies)
*Linda Hantrais, ''Managing Professional and Family Life: A Comparative Study of British and French Women''
*Deborah J. Swiss and Judith P. Walker, ''Women and the Work/Family Dilemma: How Today's Professional Women Are Finding Solutions''
*Alice M. Yohalem, ''The Careers of Professional Women: Commitment and Conflict''

;Workplace discrimination based on gender
*The Commission on Women in the Profession, ''Sex-Based Harassment, 2nd Edition: Workplace Policies for the Legal Profession''
*Sylvia Ann Hewlett, ''Off-ramps and On-ramps: Keeping Talented Women on the Road to Success''
*Karen Maschke, ''The Employment Context'' (Gender and American Law: The Impact of the Law on the Lives of Women)
*Evelyn Murphy and E. J. Graff, ''Getting Even: Why Women Don't Get Paid Like Men—And What to Do About It'' (2006)
*KOLHATKAR, SHEELAH, "THE DISRUPTERS" ''New Yorker'', 0028792X, 11/20/2017, Vol. 93, Issue 37

;Mentoring and "old-boys/old-girls networks"
*Nancy W. Collins, ''Professional Women and Their Mentors: A Practical Guide to Mentoring for the Woman Who Wants to Get Ahead''
*Carolyn S. Duff, ''Learning From Other Women: How to Benefit From the Knowledge, Wisdom, and Experience of Female Mentors''
*Joan Jeruchim, ''Women, Mentors, and Success''
*Peggy A. Pritchard, ''Success Strategies for Women in Science: A Portable Mentor'' (Continuing Professional Development Series)

;Arts and literature studies on women in the workforce
*Carmen Rose Marshall, ''Black Professional Women in Recent American Fiction''

===Professional areas===
;Teaching, librarianship, and university professions
*Maenette K. P. Benham and Joanne Cooper, ''Let My Spirit Soar!: Narratives of Diverse Women in School Leadership (1-Off)''
*Roger Blanpain and Ann Numhauser-Henning, ''Women in Academia and Equality Law: Aiming High, Falling Short? Denmark, France, Germany, Hungary, Italy, the Netherlands, Sweden, United Kingdom'' (Bulletin of Comparative Labour Relations)
*S. A. L. Cavanagh, The Gender of Professionalism and Occupational Closure: the management of tenure-related disputes by the 'Federation of Women Teachers' Associations of Ontario' 1918–1949, Gender and Education, 15.1, March 2003, pp.&amp;nbsp;39–57. See [http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/routledg/cgee/2003/00000015/00000001/art00004 Routledge].
*Regina Cortina and Sonsoles San Roman, ''Women and Teaching: Global Perspectives on the Feminization of a Profession''
*Nancy Hoffman, ''Woman's "True" Profession'', 2nd ed.  (1982, 2nd ed.) ("classic history of women and the teaching profession in the United States")
*Julia Kwong, Ma Wanhua, and Wanhua Ma, ''Chinese Women and the Teaching Profession''

;Social sciences
*Kathleen Bowman and Larry Soule, ''New Women in Social Sciences'' (1980)
*Lynn McDonald, ''The Women Founders of the Social Sciences'' (1994)

;Social sciences – anthropology
*[[Barbara A. Babcock (folklorist)|Barbara A. Babcock]] and Nancy J. Parezo, ''Daughters of the Desert: Women Anthropologists and the Native American Southwest, 1880–1980'' (1988)
*Ruth Behar and Deborah A. Gordon, ''Women Writing Culture'' (1996)
*Maria G. Cattell and Marjorie M. Schweitzer, ''Women in Anthropology: Autobiographical Narratives and Social History'' (2006)
*Ute D. Gacs, Aisha Khan, Jerrie McIntyre, and Ruth Weinberg, ''Women Anthropologists: Selected Biographies'' (1989);''Women Anthropologists: A Biographical Dictionary'' (1988)
*Nancy Parezo, ''Hidden Scholars: Women Anthropologists and the Native American'' (1993)

;Social sciences – archaeology
*Cheryl Claassen, ''Women in Archaeology'' (1994)
*Margarita Diaz-Andreu and Marie Louise Stig Sorensen, ''Excavating Women: A History of Women in European Archaeology'' (1998;2007)
*Getzel M. Cohen and Martha Sharp Joukowsky, editors, ''Breaking Ground: Pioneering Women Archaeologists'' (2004)
*Nancy Marie White, [[Lynne P. Sullivan]], and Rochelle A. Marrinan, ''Grit-Tempered: Early Women Archaeologists in Southeastern United States'' (2001)

;Social sciences – history
*Eileen Boris and Nupur Chaudhuri, ''Voices of Women Historians: The Personal, the Political, the Professional'' (1999)
*Jennifer Scanlon and Shaaron Cosner, ''American Women Historians, 1700s–1990s: A Biographical Dictionary'' (1996)
*Nadia Smith, ''A "Manly Study"?: Irish Women Historians, 1868–1949'' (2007)
*Deborah Gray White, ''Telling Histories: Black Women Historians in the Ivory Tower'' (forthcoming 2008)
*[http://www.h-net.org/~sawh/sawh.htm Southern Association for Women Historians]

;Social sciences – linguistics
*Davison, ''The Cornell Lectures: Women in the Linguistics Profession''

;"STEM" fields (science, technology, engineering, and maths)
*Violet B. Haas and Carolyn C. Perrucci, ''Women in Scientific and Engineering Professions'' (Women and Culture Series)
*[[Patricia Clark Kenschaft]], ''Change Is Possible: Stories of Women and Minorities in Mathematics''
*[[Jacquelyn Mattfeld|Jacquelyn A. Mattfeld]] and Carol E. Van Aken, ''Women and the Scientific Professions: The MIT Symposium on American Women in Science and Engineering'' (1964 symposium;1976 publication)
*Karen Mahony &amp; Brett Van Toen, Mathematical Formalism as a Means of Occupational Closure in Computing—Why "Hard" Computing Tends to Exclude Women, Gender and Education, 2.3, 1990, pp.&amp;nbsp;319–31. See [http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ422280&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=eric_accno&amp;accno=EJ422280 ERIC record.]
*Peggy A. Pritchard, ''Success Strategies for Women in Science: A Portable Mentor'' (Continuing Professional Development Series)
*Margaret W. Rossiter, ''Women Scientists in America: Struggles and Strategies to 1940'' (Women Scientists in America)
*Otha Richard Sullivan and [[James Haskins|Jim Haskins]], ''Black Stars: African American Women Scientists and Inventors''

;Legal professions
*Joan Brockman and Dorothy E. Chunn, "'A new order of things': women's entry into the legal profession in British Columbia", ''The Advocate''
*The Commission on Women in the Profession, ''Visible Invisibility: Women of Color in Law Firms''
*The Commission on Women in the Profession, ''Sex-Based Harassment, 2nd Edition: Workplace Policies for the Legal Profession''
*Hedda Garza, ''Barred from the Bar: A History of Women in the Legal Profession'' (Women Then—Women Now)
*Jean Mckenzie Leiper, ''Bar Codes: Women in the Legal Profession''
*Sheila McIntyre and Elizabeth Sheehy, ''Calling for Change: Women, Law, and the Legal Profession''
*Mary Jane Mossman, ''The First Women Lawyers: A Comparative Study of Gender, Law And the Legal Professions''
*Rebecca Mae Salokar and Mary L. Volcansek, ''Women in Law: A Bio-Bibliographical Sourcebook''
*Ulrike Schultz and Gisela Shaw, ''Women in the World's Legal Professions'' (Onati International Series in Law and Society)
*Lisa Sherman, Jill Schecter, and Deborah Turchiano, ''Sisters-In-Law: an Uncensored Guide for Women Practicing Law in the real world''

;Religious professions
*Stanley J. Grenz and Denise Muir Kjesbo, ''Women in the Church: A Biblical Theology of Women in Ministry''
*Lenore Friedman, ''Meetings with Remarkable Women: Buddhist Teachers in America''

;Helping professions (social work, childcare, eldercare, etc.)
*Ski Hunter, Sandra Stone Sundel, and Martin Sundel, ''Women at Midlife: Life Experiences and Implications for the Helping Professions''
*Linda Reeser, Linda Cherrey, and Irwin Epstein, ''Professionalization and Activism in Social Work'' (1990) (covers gender as part of history of professionalization), Columbia University Press, {{ISBN|0-231-06788-7}}
*Sarah Stage and Virginia B. Vincenti, editors, ''Rethinking Home Economics: Women and the History of a Profession''

;Architecture and design
*'' Designing for Diversity: Gender, Race, and Ethnicity in the Architectural Profession'' by [[Kathryn H. Anthony]]
*''The First American Women Architects'' by Sarah Allaback (forthcoming 2008)

;Arts and literature
*Margaret Barlow, ''[[Women Artists]]''
*[[Whitney Chadwick]], ''Women Artists and the Surrealist Movement''
*[[Liz Rideal]], [[Whitney Chadwick]], and [[Frances Borzello]], ''Mirror Mirror: Self-Portraits by Women Artists''
*Jo Franceschina, ''Women and the Profession of Theater, 1810–1860''
*[[National Geographic Society]], ''Women Photographers at National Geographic''
*Laura R. Prieto, ''At Home in the Studio: The Professionalization of Women Artists in America''

;Entertainment and modeling
*Ann Cvetkovich, "Fierce Pussies and Lesbian Avengers: Dyke Activism Meets Celebrity Culture" (images of female models merging infiltrating other cultures)
*Michael Gross, ''Model: The Ugly Business of Beautiful Women'' (2003) (history of female modeling);
*Ian Halperin, ''Shut Up and Smile: Supermodels, the Dark Side'' (1999)
*Nancy Hellmich, "Do thin models warp girls' body image?", ''USA Today'', September 26, 2006
*Jennifer Melocco, "Ban on Stick-Thin Models Illegal", ''Daily Telegraph'', February 16, 2007
*[[Barbara Summers]], ''Black and Beautiful: How Women of Color Changed the Fashion Industry'' (racism within modeling)
*Barbara Summers, ''Skin Deep: Inside the World of Black Fashion Models'' (1999)
*[[Naomi Wolf]], ''[[The Beauty Myth|The Beauty Myth: How Images of Beauty Are Used Against Women]]'' (1991)

;Explorers, navigators, travelers, settlers
*Joanna Stratton, ''Pioneer Women''
*David Cordingly, ''Seafaring Women: Adventures of Pirate Queens, Female Stowaways, and Sailors' Wives''

;Sports and athletics
*Karra Porter, ''Mad Seasons: The Story of the First Women's Professional Basketball League, 1978–1981''

;Business and leadership
*Roger E. Axtell, Tami Briggs, Margaret Corcoran, and Mary Beth Lamb, ''Do's and Taboos Around the World for Women in Business''
*Douglas Branson, ''No Seat at the Table: How Corporate Governance and Law Keep Women Out of the Boardroom''
*Lin Coughlin, Ellen Wingard, and Keith Hollihan, ''Enlightened Power: How Women are Transforming the Practice of Leadership''
*Harvard Business School Press, editors, ''Harvard Business Review on Women in Business''
*S. N. Kim, "Racialized gendering of the accountancy profession: toward an understanding of Chinese women's experiences in accountancy in New Zealand" in ''[[Critical Perspectives on Accounting]]''
*Deborah Rhode, ''The Difference ""Difference"" Makes: Women and Leadership'' (2002)
*Judy B. Rosener, ''America's Competitive Secret: Women Managers''
*Robert E. Seiler, ''Women in the Accounting Profession'' (1986)

;European Union initiatives and information
*[http://ec.europa.eu/employment_social/publications/2008/ke8108186_en.pdf Report "Women and men in decision-making 2007 – analysis of the situation and trends"]
*[http://ec.europa.eu/employment_social/women_men_stats/index_en.html Database on women in decision-making]
*[http://ec.europa.eu/employment_social/gender_equality/gender_mainstreaming/roadmap_en.html Commission's Roadmap for Equality between women and men (2006–2010)]

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
* from the collections of the [[Imperial War Museum]]
*[http://www.radcliffe.harvard.edu/event/2011new-majority "The New Majority? the Past, Present and Future of Women in the Workplace"], Symposium at [[Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study]], September 9, 2011.
*[http://ccdl.libraries.claremont.edu/cdm/landingpage/collection/p15831coll7 Women's Employment, United States and Great Britain in the Early 20th Century] in the Claremont Colleges Digital Library 
*[https://fraser.stlouisfed.org/theme/73 A collection of historical documents chronicling the role of women in the nation's economy and labor force], with statistical reports and other documents coming from sources such as the Census Bureau, the Supreme Court, the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights and the Women's Bureau.
*[http://www.adb.org/features/empowering-enterprising-women-asia Women in Business and Commerce in Asia], Asian Development Bank
* [https://www.aauw.org  American Association of University Women]

{{Africa topic|Women in}}
{{Asia topic|Women in}}
{{North America topic|Women in}}
{{South America topic|Women in}}
{{Oceania topic|Women in}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Women In The Workforce}}
[[Category:Women's studies]]
[[Category:Women by occupation|Women by occupation]]
[[Category:Employment discrimination]]
[[Category:Women's occupational organizations|*]]
[[Category:Women and employment]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>